<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sober answer to an angry epistle, directed to all the publick teachers in this nation, and prefixed to a book, called (by an antiphrasis) Christs innocency pleaded against the cry of the chief priests. Written in hast by Thomas Speed, once a publick teacher himself, and since revolted from that calling to merchandize, and of late grown a merchant of soules, trading subtilly for the Quakers in Bristoll. Wherein the jesuiticall equivocations and subtle insinuations, whereby he endeavours secretly to infuse the whole venome of Quaking doctrines, into undiscerning readers, are discovered; a catlogue of the true and genuine doctrines of the Quakers is presented, and certaine questions depending between us and them, candidly disputed, / by [brace] Christopher Fowler &amp; Simon Ford, [brace] ministers of the Gospel in Reding,</title>
            <author>Fowler, Christopher, 1610?-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E883_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207293</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866352</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866352</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84760)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E883[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sober answer to an angry epistle, directed to all the publick teachers in this nation, and prefixed to a book, called (by an antiphrasis) Christs innocency pleaded against the cry of the chief priests. Written in hast by Thomas Speed, once a publick teacher himself, and since revolted from that calling to merchandize, and of late grown a merchant of soules, trading subtilly for the Quakers in Bristoll. Wherein the jesuiticall equivocations and subtle insinuations, whereby he endeavours secretly to infuse the whole venome of Quaking doctrines, into undiscerning readers, are discovered; a catlogue of the true and genuine doctrines of the Quakers is presented, and certaine questions depending between us and them, candidly disputed, / by [brace] Christopher Fowler &amp; Simon Ford, [brace] ministers of the Gospel in Reding,</title>
                  <author>Fowler, Christopher, 1610?-1678.</author>
                  <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Gellibrand, at the Ball in Pauls Church Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Speed, Thomas.  Christ's innocency pleaded against the cry of the chief priests, or, a reply unto certain papers received from William Thomas.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Speed, Thomas, b. 1622 or 3. --  Christ's innocency pleaded against the cry of the chief priests --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118623:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118623:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SOBER ANSWER To an angry EPISTLE, Directed to all the publick <hi>Teachers</hi> in this Nation, and prefixed to a Book, called (By an <hi>ANTIPHRASIS) Chriſts Innocency pleaded againſt the Cry of the Chief Prieſts.</hi> Written in haſt By THOMAS SPEED, once a publick Teacher himſelf, and ſince revolted from that Calling to <hi>Merchandize,</hi> and of late grown a <hi>Merchant</hi> of <hi>Soules,</hi> trading ſubtilly for the QUAKERS in <hi>Briſtoll.</hi> WHEREIN The Jeſuiticall Equivocations and ſubtle Inſinuations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he endeavours ſecretly to infuſe the whole Venome of <hi>Quaking Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> into undiſcerning Readers, are diſcovered; a Catalogue of the true and genuine Doctrines of the Quakers is preſented, and certaine Queſtions depending between us and them, candidly diſputed, By <hi>Chriſtopher Fowler</hi> &amp; <hi>Simon Ford,</hi> Miniſters of the Goſpel in <hi>Reding,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand,</hi> at the Ball in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church Yard, 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118623:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118623:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Colonell</hi> WILLIAM SYDENHAM, <hi>One of his</hi> Highneſs Councill, <hi>and one of the Commiſsioners for the Exchequer, and Captaine for the Iſle of WIGHT.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Author of the Paper we herein deale withall, having by his Apoſtacy to the damnable Doctrines of the Quakers, and written Apologie for them in the ſaid Paper, endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered divers of our Towne, and the parts adjacent, where he was formerly in ſome eſteem; and withall in the ſame Paper, formed into the modell of an Epiſtle directed to them, inſolently challenged all the <hi>Publick Teachers of this Nation;</hi> and particularly us, who now appeare againſt him, by ſending two of the Pamphlets to us by name; we dared not betray the Truth and Glory of our Lord Jeſus, nor the precious Soules of the People, by neglecting to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a timely <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt the Poyſon of ſuch a ſubtill and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating peice, as your Honour, if you will vouch-ſafe to look on it, and compare it with this Anſwer, will eaſily diſcerne it to be. We perceive the deſigne of the Author, is by falſe ſuggeſtions to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Miniſtry, and by Jeſuiticall Equivocation, to ſweeten
<pb facs="tcp:118623:3"/> the Doctrines of the Quakers to the Publick Magiſtrates. And upon that account, we thought it meete to preſent this our neceſſary vindication of that, and diſcovery of theſe, to ſome Perſon in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, of Honour and Conſcience; that under ſuch a ſhelter, we might gaine it a more facile admiſſion to others, of thoſe unto whom we are neceſſitated to appeale. And becauſe we can aſſuredly ſuite that Character to your ſelf; and withall are perſwaded, that by reaſon of your equability of carriage to diſſenters in late times, our Adverſary himſelf cannot reaſonably quarrell at us, for our choyce of a Patron; and laſtly becauſe we have both of us in ſome meaſure (but one of us more largely, by divers years experience) known you a cardial friend to a Godly Miniſtry, and the Doctrine which is according to Godlyneſſe; we therefore humbly put it into your Honours hands. Sir, as to the Cauſe we maintaine, we need not any <hi>Creatures Patronage,</hi> nor dare we ſubmit it to any <hi>Creatures Umpirage;</hi> for we are aſſured it (mainly) concernes ſuch founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Religion, as deeply ingage the honour of our Lord Jeſus, and therefore we are aſſured, he will not ſuffer them to be moved; and ſuch as will ſtand, when all Perſons and Doctrines ſhall be judged finally, and everlaſtingly according to the purport of them. But as to our candour and integrity in the managery thereof, and the proportion of ſatisfaction which we give therein, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to ſtand to your Arbitration, wherein however we may fare, yet it ſhall ſuffice us, that our Conſciences tell us, that we have done our endeavour to defend the Truth, and that with meekneſſe and moderation, beyond our Antagoniſts deſerts, or the merits of his cauſe; and our experience tells us, that you will not diſdain to accept from us this ſmall Teſtimony, that we are very much,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(Right Honourable)</salute>
               <signed>Your Honours affectionate Servants for the Intereſt of Chriſt our Maſter,
<list>
                     <item>Simon Ford.</item>
                     <item>Chriſtopher Fowler.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118623:3"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO AN EPISTLE OF <hi>THOMAS SPEED,</hi> Directed to all the Publick TEACHERS in this Nation, and prefixed to a Book of his called by an <hi>ANTIPHRASIS, Chriſt's Innocency pleaded,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT many daies ſince, we received each of us a Book as from you, by the hands of a Friend of yours, living in this Town, Intituled <hi>Chriſts Innocency pleaded, &amp;c.</hi> which although it be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly directed to a Godly and able Miniſter of the Neighbourhood, yet it ſeems you thought fit to diſperſe it into theſe parts, as well as over the reſt of the Nation, in Print, to confirm thoſe that are already gained to your belief, and reduce others either to an entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118623:4"/> of, or moderation to, the principles thereof. And we muſt confeſſe, that you have acted the laſt part of this deſigne with a great deale of Artifice, not without (as we conceive) a concurrent aime of your own, to ſhew how much credit your wit could give to an evill cauſe, and how (if not <hi>amiable,</hi> yet) <hi>tolerable,</hi> you could render an ugly face, by a decent dreſſe.</p>
            <p>For our parts, we are ſorry you can find no better exerciſe for your parts, then the maintaining of abſurd Paradoxes in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, and blaſphemous Hereſies in Religion; for ſo we dare call the Doctrines you undertake to ſhelter under the wing of your Patronage; and make no queſtion but that Judge, who, we are aſſured, will one day make that written Law, which you refuſe to own as the rule of your lives, the ground of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings upon you, and all others that live within the ſound of it, after death, will then call them ſo too, when all the rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call vailes you put upon them, will be pulled off, and you be found, except you repent, one of thoſe that dawbe a rotten Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher with <hi>untempered Morter,</hi> and <hi>cover Violence</hi> with a <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Garment</hi> of ſubtle and Jeſuiticall equivocation.</p>
            <p>And indeed, that which makes us the more compaſſionate towards your ſelf in this ſad deluſion you are under, is the repute which you have had (till of late daies) for ſoundneſſe and Orthodoxy in Doctrinals, and ſome kind of moderation, beyond others of your Brethren in ſeparation, towards thoſe you ſeparated from: And this, becauſe we feare that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of your Apoſtacy may occaſion the ruine of many others, whoſe former eſteem of your perſon endangers them to follow you blindfold into your Errors.</p>
            <p>This, we aſſure you, is not the leaſt cauſe (together with the preſervation of thoſe of our own charges from the infection likely to be ſpread among them by your name, and the reduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe of them who may (we feare) call you Father, in other reſpects, as well as the relation of Affinity) which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth us to put Pen to paper in this Quarrell. Not that we intend hereby to take the Cudgels out of the hand of that <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend man</hi> who is more neerly concerned, and better able to manage them then our ſelves; for (as to that concernes his Papers ſo brokenly quoted by you) we believe his own publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118623:4"/> of the entire Copies (which you think fit to conceale, not without ſome ground of ſuſpicion, that you were rather willing to pick out what you could beſt ſport your ſelf, and your credulous Reader withall, then to give a ſolid anſwer to his Arguments as they come from his hand) with ſuch animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, as he is ſufficiently able to make to the diſingenuities of your reply, will abundantly vindicate him, and the Truth. Onely, we cannot but acquaint you, that you have miſtaken the mark very much in the arrowes of bitter words, which your diſcourſe levels with too much virulency againſt that holy man. Had you dealt with one of thoſe <hi>ſorry things in black,</hi> whoſe Doctrine and life are ſcandals to the Goſpell; and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes to their holy Profeſſion, you might have promiſed your ſelfe an eaſie beliefe from the Readers of your Book, to whatſoever load of reproches, you ſhould have laid upon him: but the man you deale withall, is ſo well known for Piety, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Humility, Heavenly-mindedneſſe, tenderneſſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and all other Miniſteriall Qualifications, that you may as well perſwade them the Snow is black, as faſten thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches upon him with any hope of gaining credit to your ſelf, or your book, except amongſt thoſe who are either totally ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to him, or given up to ſo potent a prejudice againſt all that beare the name of Miniſters, that they can eaſily admit into their <hi>Creed,</hi> whatſoever evill can be ſaid of them. But to more ſober Readers, and eſpecially thoſe of the parts where he lives, you might be eaſily convinced (had you any principles left to bottome a conviction upon) that the unjuſt imputations you every where beſpatter him withall, will render you ſuſpected, in all the reſt of your book, for the falſehood detected in them. And we muſt tel you withal, that we cannot prevail w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>h our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or conſciences to perſwade themſelves that you have that <hi>infallible Spirit,</hi> which you pretend to dictate to you; ſeeing we know you to be ſo groſsly miſtaken in the cenſures you ſpend upon him, and divers of his fellow-labourers. Nor can we judge that language inſpired by the holy ſpirit of God, when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, that there is no <hi>Gall</hi> in that <hi>Dove,</hi> &amp; that thoſe holy men of God who <hi>wrote as they were moved by the H. Ghoſt,</hi> tell us, that <hi>Saints muſt put away all clamour and bitterneſſe; and evill ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 31.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118623:5"/> 
               <hi>and wrath:</hi> That <hi>the wiſdome that is from above is gentle;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ja. 3. 17. Ja. 1. 16.</note> and that <hi>if any man bridle not his tongue, his religion is vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, that if you be not a better Maſter of Language then <hi>Michal</hi> the Arch-angel, or we deſerve worſe uſage then the <hi>Devill</hi> himſelf; the light in which the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> ſpake, will tell you (but that you think him too low a Scholar to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you, that have gotten through the Schoole, wherein he was a Diſciple) that it ill becomes you to bring againſt your Antagoniſts a <hi>railing accuſation.</hi> But if that convince not you <note place="margin">Iude 9.</note> and your brethren of the incivility and irreligion of your tongues and pens in this way, we ſhall refer you from <hi>Michaels Diſpute</hi> to <hi>Enochs Propheſie,</hi> wherein you will find, that <hi>hard ſpeeches</hi> will beare an Indictment at the laſt Aſſiſe, as well as <note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> 
               <hi>hard blowes:</hi> And in the mean time, we hope God will heare our prayers, and free us from the mercy of your <hi>Hands,</hi> who find what <hi>cruelty</hi> there is in the <hi>tender mercies</hi> of your <note place="margin">Prov. 12. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Tongues</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mean while, in hope that a <hi>ſoft anſwer will turn away wrath,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 1.</note> and that we may ſet you a fairer Copy to write after, when you next put pen to paper, we ſhall endeavour by Gods aſſiſtance, <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 4, 5.</note> to anſwer ſo much of your papers, as concernes us in common with other Miniſters, without anſwering your paſſions.</p>
            <p>And Sir, upon our firſt view of your Pamphlet, we cannot <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</note> but tell you, that if your <hi>Title-page</hi> were calculated for the Meridian of your Book, you miſtook your ſelf extreamly: For <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tituli re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media, pix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ides vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi>
               </note> (to let paſſe the Title it ſelf, wherein you abuſe the glorious name of <hi>Chriſts Innocency,</hi> to patronize your own <hi>guilt)</hi> we cannot but wonder how <hi>Seneca</hi> (an Heathen) comes to be ſo great in your eſteem, that you that will not allow us to quote <hi>Hierome, Auguſtine, Calvin,</hi> or <hi>Luther,</hi> yet think your Book <note place="margin">Epiſtle p. D.</note> credited by the wreſted Teſtimony of a Pagan Philoſopher pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed thereunto. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But to let that paſſe, and proceed to your <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe you direct it to the whole body of the Miniſtery, we ſuppoſe our ſelves concerned in. The reſt of your Book, becauſe we are aſſured from your Adverſary that he will ſpeedily take it in hand; we ſuppoſe you will give us leave to be ſo ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as to leave to his able Pen, without interpreting it any wiſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118623:5"/> to proceed from any conſciouſneſſe of our own weakneſſe, that we meddle not with it.</p>
            <p>And here in the firſt place, we con you many thanks for the charitable advice you begin withall, and aſſure you, that the more we think of <hi>the day and houre,</hi> which in your entrance you mind us of, and that <hi>account</hi> we muſt hereafter therein give to the <hi>righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth,</hi> the more are we exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the conſciencious diſcharge of that office, which (howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you revile) we are ſufficiently aſſured he will own at that day to be held by commiſſion from him: and the more are we encouraged againſt all that evill entertainment, which (for the diſcharge thereof) we meet withall, from <hi>men of corrupt minds,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>reprobate as concerning the Faith.</hi> And we hope, we ſhall take warning (even from an Adverſary) to <hi>walk worthy of our high and holy calling,</hi> and not wear our <hi>Livery</hi> to the diſgrace of our <hi>Maſter.</hi> But we are jealous, that whatever uſe we may make of your counſell, you intend it to far another purpoſe; to wit, rather as a ſlye way of caſting reproach upon us, by inſinuating that we ſtand in need of being ſo adviſed, then out of any inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to do us good by that advice. <hi>[I wiſh you were</hi>] (in your language) is no other, then <hi>[I proclaime your are not:</hi>] <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</note> And although you tell us immediatly after, that <hi>you will not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſtle, pag.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>raſhly to judge us, or accuſe us to the world</hi> (from which crime of <hi>raſh judgment</hi> you think your ſelf ſufficiently ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by comparing our works with <hi>our rule, the Scriptures)</hi> and then proceed (as you think <hi>cum privilegio)</hi> to miſapply Scriptures, to ſlander us, yet we muſt retort upon you that which you give in way of advice to us, that the <hi>hower is coming, when all coverings ſhall be removed, and the vailes pluckt off from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep. p.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>all faces;</hi> and then we doubt not but you will be found, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>raſh,</hi> but a <hi>falſe accuſer,</hi> and that <hi>to the world</hi> (in Print) notwithſtanding that colour and covering which you hide it withall.</p>
            <p>For do you believe in earneſt, that thoſe Prophets of whom <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Micah</hi> ſpeaks, that <hi>teach for hire, and divine for money,</hi> or thoſe <note place="margin">Mic. 3, 11. Mar. 23. 5, 6, 7.</note> whom our Saviour notes, for <hi>doing their works to be ſeen of men, for ſtanding to pray in the Synagogues and the corners of the ſtreets for loving the uppermoſt roomes at Feaſts, &amp;c.</hi> are chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118623:6"/> ſuiting the <hi>men of your indignation,</hi> whom you endeavour to degrade from the eſteem they have, as Miniſters of Chriſt, by ſuch intimations as theſe? You pretend to ſomething of Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larſhip and reaſon, and cannot but know, except your <hi>new</hi> light have quite put out the old, that the Prieſts and Prophets that <hi>Micah</hi> ſpeaks of were ſuch, as made their <hi>hire</hi> the end of their <hi>teaching</hi> and <hi>propheſying,</hi> and accordingly accommodated their Doctrines to the corrupt humours of thoſe, from whom they expected their reward; a thing which a fixed maintenance, by Tithes, or otherwiſe by Law eſtabliſhed, ſecures our Miniſters from the tentation of.</p>
            <p>It is you, and your brethren that would <hi>make us</hi> ſuch as you <hi>ſlander us to be,</hi> by reducing us to voluntary contributions, which would be quickly detained from us, as often as we ſhould dare to differ from the opinions, or reprove the Vices of our Neighbours.</p>
            <p>And who are you, <hi>Sir,</hi> that judge our hearts, when you tell <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</note> us, what we aime at, and ſet up as our end in teaching, which you do more then once, and twice in your Epiſtle, and Book? How long have you been ſeated in the Throne of the moſt high God, and made a Judge of the <hi>ſecrets of mens hearts,</hi> that you tell us that we <hi>preach for hire,</hi> and <hi>do our works to be ſeen of men,</hi> and <hi>that we love the upper-moſt roomes, &amp;c.</hi> As for <hi>ſtanding to pray in the Synagogues,</hi> if you conſult the place whence you pretend to draw that parallell between the Phariſees and us, you will find that the action is not condemned, but the end, <hi>to be ſeen of men;</hi> they neglecting in the mean time to pray in their <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 5.</note> Cloſets, where man could not take notice of their devotion. And ſo this charge (except you will ſay, with ſome of your companions, that <hi>you know the heart)</hi> comes under the ſame <note place="margin">G. Fox <hi>ſee the perfect Phariſee, p.</hi> 49. <hi>and</hi> 4.</note> condemnation of ſlander with the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The corners of the ſtreets,</hi> if they be uſed by any perſons in theſe daies, for religious uſes, we know not who herein reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> more then thoſe of your own Fraternity (and Siſterhood too) who, though they meddle little with prayer, (it is to be ſeared) any where, yet chooſe the ſtreets, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-places to vent their pretended Declarations from God.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118623:6"/>
            <p>Your <hi>next Paragraph</hi> endeavours to faſten upon <hi>us</hi> the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</note> of <hi>Perſecuters,</hi> and <hi>upon your ſelves</hi> the character of <hi>Chriſtian ſufferers.</hi> To which, we ſhall ſay only thus much in this place, That we adore that gracious Providence which keeps us out of the reach of your malice; otherwiſe we are aſſured we ſhould not be long without that perſecution which you make the badge of true Miniſters, for better Doctrines and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, then thoſe, which ſome of yours ſuffer for.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, we have our ſhares ſufficiently in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of your tongues, and hands, as far as you can, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhing us, and our Families, by detaining our juſt and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſubſiſtence, diſturbing us in the exerciſe of our publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which we ſuffer conſtantly from thoſe of your fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and communion. What further needs to be ſpoken to this head, as it concernes your uſage from us, will be taken up in its due place, and more largely debated with you hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Sect. 9, 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That we are not the Miniſters of Chriſt, becauſe we <hi>indent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>for our maintenance,</hi> where we ſit down in a charge, and that we <hi>ſue for the tenth of their increaſe, thoſe that owne us not for their Paſtors,</hi> is the ſumme of your <hi>charge.</hi> To the firſt branch whereof, we can, divers of us, reject it as a meer ſlander: many Miniſters in this Nation living upon as free a contribution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maintenance, as any of your ſelves, but in a more orderly way; Their people contribute to thoſe Paſtors that reſide among them, and not to wandering Preachers, whoſe faces they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſee, and from whoſe ſtanding converſe with, or inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over them they can receive no benefit. And others of us maintain many <hi>Lectures,</hi> either ſimply, or joyntly, for which we receive as little, as the <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves would wiſh. And as for thoſe that either indent for maintenance, or enter upon the maintenance already ſetled by Law; we are ſure they are not blame-worthy, for that, to gain the repute of <hi>Miniſters,</hi> they do not prove themſeles <hi>worſe then Infidells,</hi> in not provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for <hi>themſelves</hi> and their Families, which the Apoſtles light makes a badge of <hi>one that hath denied the faith</hi> (the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 8.</note> character of ſome of yours, who wander up and down to the manifeſt and apparent ruine of themſelves, and thoſe that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118623:7"/> they are bound to provide for.) Nor are we at all ſtartled at the practiſe of the Apoſtles under an <hi>extraordinary command,</hi> ſo confeſſed (in effect) by your ſelves in your own practiſe, (for why elſe do you not travell about to declare without <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> or <hi>Shooes on your feet,</hi> or <hi>Staves in your hands,</hi> commands immediatly ſubjoyning to that of <hi>giving freely what they had</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 8, 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>freely received,</hi> in the ſame place of Scripture) and appearing to be ſuch; if we compare <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 36. where Chriſt in another exigency of time allowes them to make that proviſion for <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> which in the former command he forbad them. For we are ſufficiently aſſured, that the Apoſtles themſelves were main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Church in which they laboured, excepting only the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and his companion <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and that only <note place="margin">Act. 20. 34 <hi>See</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 7. v. 9. <hi>and</hi> 2 Theſ. 3. 8, 9.</note> at <hi>Epheſus, Corinth,</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> where (little to their credit too, if we mark the tart reflexions of the Apoſtle upon their ſordidneſſe) they <hi>wrought with their hands,</hi> for ſpeciall reaſons aſſigned in the Texts themſelves; yet withall the ſaid Apoſtle aſſerts it as <hi>an Ordinance of God</hi> (and that founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaſon, and Scripture too) that <hi>they that preach the Gospel ſhould live by the Goſpel;</hi> and withall affirmeth his <hi>owne and his brethrens power</hi> to have claimed the ſame from them, which they received from other Churches. We forbeare tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing Texts, you may find this and more, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 9. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9 from <hi>verſe</hi> 6. to the end of the 14. which Scripture we obſerve in moſt of the Pamphlets publiſhed by the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Miniſters maintenance, is paſſed over with deep ſilence; and ſo expect it will be by you and your brotherhood, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by (the common refuge of Hereticks) <hi>the decrying of interpretations, and inferences upon Scripture.</hi> When you further urge the ſame Apoſtles practiſe, againſt <hi>coveting other mens ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and gold, or apparell;</hi> We have nothing to object againſt you, provided that you will not call requiring that which is le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally <hi>our own,</hi> a coveting that which is <hi>anothers:</hi> Surely no man holds the <hi>nine</hi> parts, by firmer Law in theſe Nations, then the Miniſter claimes his <hi>tenth</hi> by: And how can it then be more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous in a Miniſter to ſue for that which is his <hi>by Law,</hi> then in others to detain it from him <hi>without Law?</hi> ſo that we feare the <hi>coveting other mens ſilver and gold</hi> will lye at yours and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118623:7"/> your brethrens doores, and you will never be able to ſweep it away.</p>
            <p>The <hi>claiming a maintenance from thoſe without,</hi> and <hi>exacting it of thoſe that never heare us,</hi> which you further object againſt us, as a diſparagement to our Miniſteriall calling, comes under the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Sect.</hi> 18, 19, 20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> conſideration of <hi>maintenance in the way of Tithes,</hi> which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to its proper place, where it falls in your diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>That ſome who beare the name of Miniſters (and ſuch <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</note> as we no leſſe diſown, then your ſelfe) live in <hi>darkneſſe, ſwearing, &amp;c.</hi> (the declaiming againſt whom is the ſubſtance of your <hi>next Paragraph,</hi> and your <hi>fifth</hi> proof againſt our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;) we confeſſe and bewaile, and did the anger that dwels in you and your brethren extend to none but thoſe, who may juſtly come under that charge, we ſhould vvillingly joyne with you in the proſecution of them; and do it where any ſuch come within our reach. Yea vve further muſt profeſſe, vve ſhould be very glad, that ſome men in power among us, who are very favourable to your party, vvere as zealous againſt them as vve. We muſt freely declare that thoſe that are indeed ſuch, have been ſheltred (upon proſecution) under the vvings of ſome ſuch among us, &amp; we verily believe it is in their hearts to vviſh us all ſuch, that they might have ſome colour to ſtrike off the neck of the vvhole Miniſtry at a blow.</p>
            <p>But vve muſt tell you (whilſt vve are not all ſuch, and now fewer ſuch then formerly) that it is an injurious procedure in you, to reflect diſparagement upon a vvhole Profeſſion, for the fault of ſome that againſt their vvills joyne <hi>themſelves</hi> to them: Should all the ſwearing, drunken, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe diſorderly companions, that frequent the <hi>Quakers</hi> Aſſemblies, be reckoned among them, and <hi>all</hi> be judged by <hi>ſome,</hi> you vvould think it hard uſage. We hope you vvill be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>buy</hi> by the ſame Buſhell you <hi>ſell</hi> withall.</p>
            <p>But you are fain to come off from this charge as too groſs to be generally laid upon the whole Miniſtry, with <hi>[are there not a great ſort of you ſuch?</hi>] and <hi>[are your hands all cleane from this filth?</hi>] only you come in vvith an <hi>after-charge</hi> againſt the reſt in another Quaere, <hi>Viz. Among thoſe of you that have eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped that open pollution of drunkenneſſe with Wine, are you not</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118623:8"/> 
               <hi>yet intoxicated with wrath, and rage againſt the innocent.</hi> And you proceed, enquiring, <hi>Whether in the Priſons and Dungeons of</hi> England, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt doth not as truly lye bound by our inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and procurement</hi> (to wit, in thoſe deare Servants of his the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who <hi>account it no robbery to be</hi> at leaſt <hi>equall</hi> with their Maſter) <hi>as he did by the procurement of</hi> Saul <hi>in</hi> Damaſcus? And yet further, <hi>Whether if any poore</hi> Jeremiah <hi>came from the Lord to beare witneſſe againſt our abominations</hi> (to vvit, in thoſe abominable practiſes of inſtructing the people againſt the delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the times, vvhich is the greateſt Antidote againſt that Plague of Error and Hereſie, that is diſperſed over all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and vvorſhiping God according to the rule of his bleſſed vvord, and the light of our own conſciences) <hi>Whether there be wanting among us a Lordly Pastor, who (in caſe the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate be ſo honeſt,</hi> (to wit, through cowardize, or luke-warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) <hi>as to refuſe) will not with his owne hands put his feet in the Stocks?</hi> To vvhich vve ſay, vve know none of our Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that take ſo much upon them, if you do, you may do vvell to diſcover them; and vve ſhould be vvell contented for their paines, to ſee them ſet there a while themſelves, till they learn to <hi>do their owne buſineſſe.</hi> And then you catechize, us further in <hi>our rule</hi> (as with ſcorne enough you often cal the Scriptures, for which we muſt reckon with you at large anon.) <hi>Whether ever the true Prophets of the Lord did perſecute or impriſon any that were differing from them in matters of Religion?</hi> And <hi>Whether they be in Chriſts eſteem Shepheards, or Wolves, who worry the Sheep inſtead of feeding them, &amp;c?</hi> After vvhich you ſpend a great deale of rhetorick in anticipating the Judgment of Chriſt at the laſt day, as if you vvere already beſpoken to be <hi>Clerk of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignments</hi> againſt that <hi>Aſſiſe:</hi> In anſwer vvhereunto vve ſay no more but this; <hi>Judge not, that yee be not judged:</hi> And vve make no queſtion, that if no better evidence be brought againſt us at that day, then any you yet offer, to prove thoſe high Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations; that our <hi>Not-guilty</hi> vvill be as good a <hi>plea</hi> (though vvithout a <hi>diſtinction)</hi> as your charge of <hi>Guilty</hi> vvill be an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment</hi> vvithout a <hi>proof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing vve vvere (indeed) the <hi>Perſecuters,</hi> the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>10</label> 
               <hi>Worriers,</hi> the <hi>Impriſoners,</hi> of thoſe <hi>men of your right hand,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118623:8"/> provided, we were legally commiſſioned thereunto (which we hope we ſhall never deſire for our ſelves, nor allow in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our Function) yet why all <hi>diſtinctions</hi> ſhould be a plea ſo inconſiſtent with the Juſtice of that Court (as you intimate to us it will be) we know not. Nay, we have a little light from <hi>(our low rule)</hi> the Scripture, that perſwades us there <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 4, 5.</note> may be ſome uſe of them then. For in that ſhort deſcription of the laſt Judgment, whence you draw out a Copy of our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment, not without ſome aggravating expoſtulations <hi>(viz. Mat.</hi> 25 41, 42. <hi>&amp;c)</hi> we find the Judge <hi>diſtinguiſhing upon the Bench,</hi> to conclude the Offenders within the reach of the Law; For the wicked there indicted are brought in pleading their <hi>Not guilty,</hi> as to the neglect of <hi>relieving and viſiting</hi> Chriſt in his <hi>own perſon.</hi> To take off which <hi>plea,</hi> and cleare the equity of his condemnatory ſentence; he diſtinguiſheth between <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his perſon,</hi> and <hi>himſelf in his little ones,</hi> or <hi>Members;</hi> and granting their plea as to the <hi>former,</hi> rejects it as to the <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Now, ſurely we cannot believe that the Judge of the whole World will not at that great and ſolemn day, give us the latitude he takes to himſelf. If he diſtinguiſh upon the <hi>Law,</hi> he will allow us to diſtinguiſh upon the <hi>Indictment.</hi> We know not if we be indicted for worrying the Sheep; why we may not plead the Scripture diſtinction between <hi>Sheep indeed,</hi> and <hi>Wolves in Sheeps clothing;</hi> and if we can indeed prove that we worry no other, but <hi>diſguiſed Wolves</hi> (upon which proof in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we are contented to lay the whole ſtreſſe of our preſent, and (we hope) future juſtification in this whole matter now in debate between us) we cannot but expect the ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge at the Bar, which we ſhould not doubt from humane e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, in caſe, being indicted for aſſaulting and beating a <hi>true Subject</hi> upon <hi>Salisbury plaines,</hi> we could make it appeare, that we beat only a <hi>Theef,</hi> and that upon our own <hi>neceſſary defence:</hi> So that indeed, all that outragious cry which you afterward make againſt the <hi>poore Presbyters</hi> for juſtifying the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and the <hi>Lordly Biſhops</hi> in former times (who, you perſwade your ſelf) had the ſame diſtinction to plead, for <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying the Lord of Glory,</hi> and his <hi>precious Saints,</hi> and <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Puritanes, &amp;c.</hi> to wit, <hi>that they uſed them thus under</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118623:9"/> 
               <hi>the notion of blaſphemous Hereticks and Deceivers)</hi> falls to the ground, if we can prove thoſe whom we are charged to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, ſuch as we take them to be. And this we doubt not to make good againſt you, and your brethren in the way of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, in the proceſſe of this our book, and then ſhall leave the whole matter to our Lord, and yours, to judge between us at the <hi>great day of his appearing.</hi> But then you will allow us <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>11</label> (we hope) not to ſuffer you to <hi>phraſe your own Indictment,</hi> as you do very dextrouſly and artificially, in favour of your ſelf and your Generation, in the <hi>following Section</hi> of your Epiſtle; wherein you make your ſelf, and your Reader pretty ſport, by drawing up a <hi>ridiculous charge</hi> againſt your ſelves, and then ſet our <hi>names</hi> to it, as if we had made <hi>ſo great a cry</hi> (as you mention) <hi>for ſo little wooll,</hi> and had no matters of greater mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>exhibit</hi> againſt you, then thoſe which you will <hi>confeſſe</hi> againſt your ſelves. And yet we muſt tell you, that you were not very well adviſed (if you meant wholly to clear your ſelves from thoſe imputations) to confeſſe ſo much as you do in many paſſages of your Book, which we ſhall deale with anon. Mean while we dare not let you alone to couſen the World in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a good eſteem of your opinions by your ambiguous expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and therefore we muſt crave your patience, if we <hi>come after you, and ſift you,</hi> that by being <hi>firſt in your owne cauſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 17.</note> you may not <hi>ſeem uprighter</hi> then indeed you are.</p>
            <p>Firſt, you take it ill to be charged as <hi>Blasphemers,</hi> for <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>12</label> affirming, <hi>that Chriſt is the light that enlighteneth every one that cometh into the world, and that he that followeth that light</hi> (your <note place="margin">Jo. 8. 2.</note> Text (by the way) ſaith, <hi>He that followeth me,</hi> and the words <hi>[that light</hi>] are your interpretation and meaning, which (were we as peeviſh as thoſe of your way) we might reject) <hi>ſhall not walk in darkneſſe, but ſhall have the light of life;</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding further, <hi>that that light is ſufficient to teach them and guide them to the Father:</hi> and thence ask for a cloſe, <hi>What need then of our teachings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We hope (ſeeing you ſtand upon your purgation) you will give us leave to ask you a few queſtions upon this Article.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Q. What light is that with which Chriſt enlightens every man? It is Chriſt himſelf</hi> (we would ſay, if you would give us
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118623:9"/> leave for diſtinction ſake) <hi>perſonally,</hi> or is it a <hi>light infuſed in him?</hi> If ſo,</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Q. It is the light of bare reaſon in a reaſonable Soule,</hi> or is it <hi>the diſcovery of himſelfe by ſupernaturall revelation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>Q.</hi> Whether the <hi>meer light of reaſon</hi> be ſufficient to lead all men, Heathens and all, to the Father <hi>ſavingly;</hi> or onely (as the place partially quoted in your next Article hath it) to <hi>that which may be known of him, by the things that are made, that they may be without excuſe?</hi> or</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Q.</hi> Whether if any meer Pagan live up to the naturall light of his own reaſon or conſcience, God be bound to beſtow upon him that farther light, which is ſufficient to bring him to ſalvation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi> 5. If Chriſt be (in your ſence) <hi>the light of every one that comes into the World;</hi> why is it that <hi>Judas</hi> ſaith <hi>Jo.</hi> 14. 23. <hi>Lord, how is it that thou wilt manifeſt thy ſelf to us, and not to the World?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when you have anſwered (plainly and without equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations) to theſe quaeres; poſſibly you may retort your <hi>clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Quaere</hi> upon your ſelves: <hi>What need then of our teachings, as well as the Prieſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You would faine make us believe (in your <hi>next Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle)</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>13</label> that you ſay no more in the caſe of the <hi>Heathens light,</hi> then the Apoſtle doth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 19. 20. which is (as you render it) <hi>That that which may be known of God is manifeſt in their conſciences</hi> (where again, though we contradict it not, yet we obſerve you can <hi>interpret,</hi> and give your <hi>meanings</hi> upon Scripture, though in us it be <hi>adding to the Scripture;</hi> for the Text ſaith no more but <hi>in them,</hi> or (as in your Margin) <hi>to them. (God having,</hi> ſay you farther, <hi>revealed it to them) [ſhewed</hi>] ſaith the Text, <hi>[revealed</hi>] is your <hi>meaning,</hi> becauſe it makes more for your own turn; <hi>ſo that they not having a Law without them</hi> (interpretation again) <hi>they are a Law to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp;c. Rom.</hi> 2. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>Now you would inſinuate, that you hold forth no more then the Scripture doth therein: Which whether you do or no, will appeare by your plaine and ingenuous anſwer to the former <hi>Quaeres.</hi> Mean while, we deſire you to take notice. 1 That
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118623:10"/> the words in the Text <hi>[That which may be known of God</hi>] im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, <hi>that there is ſomething of God which may not be known to Heathens,</hi> as ſuch; which is <hi>the way of being reconciled to him, and juſtified in his ſight, through Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and other like Goſpel diſcoveries of him, neceſſary to ſalvation. (2.) That the knowledge they have of him, is by the Apoſtle affirmed to be a light <hi>without</hi> them, as well as <hi>within</hi> them, for <hi>God ſhewes it to them by the things that are made.</hi> (3.) That if the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens (as you ſay) <hi>have only a Law within them, and none without them,</hi> we are little beholding to your principles, that would reduce us to the condition of Heathens, by ſetting up a <hi>light within us</hi> to the excluſion of a <hi>light without us.</hi> As alſo, (4.) That <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> may ſhake hands, ſeeing both of them live by the ſame Law, and the ſame light too.</p>
            <p>You further inſinuate <hi>(Artile</hi> 3.) that in the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>of perfection here below;</hi> you are falſely accuſed by us for blaſpheming: Whereas you ſay no more then our Saviour himſelf commands, when he bids us <hi>be perfect, as our Father in Heaven is perfect;</hi> which commands, you ſay, is not given in <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 48.</note> 
               <hi>mockery,</hi> or requires an <hi>impoſſibility.</hi> You add, <hi>that the ſame Chriſt spake truth, when he bore witneſſe of</hi> Nathaniel, <hi>that he was an Iſraelite in whom was no guile:</hi> and that <hi>Paul did not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Io. 1. 47.</note> 
               <hi>deſigne an impoſſibility when he laboured to preſent men perfect in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And you would ſuggeſt that you affirm no more: <note place="margin">Col. 1. 28.</note> We anſwer, whether this be all you your ſelf hold of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or no, we will not judge. But we ſhall ſhew you anon, that thoſe of your perſwaſion are not altogether ſo modeſt. It is well if your ſelf be ſo, when you will pleaſe to ſpeak out, which we ſcarce believe you will do, in a charge againſt your ſelf of your own drawing up. But we hope, you will allow us to ask you a few queſtions upon this Article alſo, ſeeing you ſtand upon your juſtification.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 1. To what purpoſe is all this? Did any of your preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Accuſers ever accuſe our Saviour Chriſt, for <hi>mockery</hi> or <hi>commanding impoſſibilities,</hi> in this command of perfection? or for <hi>falſehood</hi> in his commendation of <hi>Nathaniel?</hi> or the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul for deſigning an impoſſibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118623:10"/>
            <p>2. <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether the perfection <hi>commanded</hi> by Chriſt, or that which is <hi>commended</hi> in <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> or <hi>aimed</hi> at by <hi>Paul,</hi> be a <hi>perfection of degrees,</hi> and that as high as that of God himſelf; or a <hi>perfection of kind, truth, or ſincerity?</hi> Say not that we coine diſtinctions of perfection out of our own braine. Doth not the Scripture call <hi>Job a perfect man, Job</hi> 1. 1. and yet chap. 3. gives us a ſad inſtance of his imperfections, and <hi>Job</hi> himſelf renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth perfection in himſelf, chap. 9. 20, 21. Doth not the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, in one chapter, <hi>affirms</hi> and <hi>deny</hi> himſelf to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 12. 15. And therefore (ſeeing, as we hope, you will not allow any contradictions in Scripture) there a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to diſtinguiſh of different ſences, wherein they affirme and deny. And if we diſtinguiſh amiſſe, we wiſh you, or your companions would do it better. Nay, we ſuppoſe both theſe ſorts of perfection neceſſarily held forth in the Scriptures of your own quotation. For the command of our Saviour ſaies not, <hi>Be yee as perfect as your Father which is in Heaven,</hi> but <hi>Be yee perfect as your Father in Heaven is perfect. [Perfect as]</hi> doth not imply more then a perfection of the ſame kind, which perfection we profeſſe, a perfection conſiſting in <hi>truth and ſincerity</hi> of holineſſe, the perfection of <hi>Nathaniel [as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect]</hi> denotes a perfection of <hi>degrees,</hi> which (in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon with an infinitely holy God) we deny to be attainable by any Creature, or to be aſſerted concerning any Creature, without higheſt blaſphemy. But a perfection of degrees ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the capacity of <hi>finite Creatures,</hi> we hope for in Heaven; and a perfection of degrees ſuitable to the capacity of <hi>mortall creatures,</hi> we preſſe towards your ſelves, and endeavour with <hi>Paul, to preſent</hi> all our hearers unto Jeſus Chriſt in the ſame at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>4. About your <hi>forth Article</hi> concerning <hi>rejecting all mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>and interpretations of Scripture,</hi> we ſhall take a more convenient time to reckon with you in a diſtinct Queſtion ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned hereunto. Only we make bold to ask you here alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether <hi>[to interpret Chriſts and the Apoſtles ſayings]</hi> be not injuriouſly reflected upon by you as a deniall that <hi>they meant as they spake?</hi> and whether a man may not mean as he ſpeaks, and yet not to be underſtood without interpretation?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118623:11"/> we are ſo charitable to think that divers of the Familiſts and Quakers <hi>mean as they speak,</hi> and yet we cannot underſtand their <hi>meaning</hi> by their <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> in divers odd phraſes uſed by them, without interpretation; would you would give us a Lexicon of them.</p>
            <p>5. Your <hi>fifth Article,</hi> we ſhall ſpeak more largely to in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect</hi> 16.</note> this place. You ſay, that you and your Complices aſſert, <hi>that Chriſt did not ſpeak one thing and intend another, when he commanded men not to ſweare at all, but to let their yea, be yea, and nay, nay:</hi> Whereas we that are (ſcornfully enough) by you called <hi>Orthodox, do both ſweare our ſelves, and teach others ſo to do.</hi> And you add the reaſon (as good a one as you pleaſe to allow us) becauſe <hi>otherwiſe we might happily go without our maintenance, for want of ſwearers in Courts of Juſtice, againſt thoſe Hereticks that refuſe to pay us Tythes.</hi> And in your Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin (to give us a touch of your learning, that we may take it for an act of ſelf-deniall in your after-declared contempt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and not an act of envious declaiming againſt the Grapes you cannot reach) you quote the Originall in that prohibition, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with this note, <hi>That it is a prohibition ſo univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, that it admitteth of no exception.</hi> Upon which Article we firſt obſerve two things.</p>
            <p>1. That it was very warily done of the Founders of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Religion, who are by many judicious men ſuppoſed to be Papiſts, to inſert an Article in their new Creed, to excuſe them from being diſcovered, by refuſing the <hi>Oath of Abjuration,</hi> which they may (under the ſhelter of your Principles) do, and yet paſſe undiſcovered. <hi>Secondly</hi> we <hi>quaere,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We obſerve ſecondly, that the Quakers refuſing to ſweare according to the Ceremony now required in <hi>England,</hi> of <hi>kiſſing the Bible,</hi> and ſwearing <hi>by the contents of that Book,</hi> is ſuitable to their Doctrine; <hi>that the Scriptures are not our rule,</hi> and (by conſequence that God will not judge us according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Bible; ſo that to call God to witneſſe according to the contents of that book, according to which they conceive he will not judge, were abſurd. It may be if a new forme of an <hi>Oath,</hi> ſuch as <hi>by the light within them,</hi> were required, they might be perſwaded to ſweare.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118623:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 1. Whether our Saviour Chriſt <hi>ſpake or intended</hi> any thing which might claſh with the expreſſe command of God elſewhere? And if not, then ſurely Chriſts words in this place muſt not be taken ſo unlimitedly as you ſay, ſeeing we find a command <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt feare the Lord thy God, and ſweare by his name.</hi> So alſo <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 2. Whether our Saviour Chriſt forbid any part of Gods morall Worſhip, or no? If not, then we are aſſured he forbids <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Jer. 4. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> Iſ. 45. 23. <hi>which peculiarly concerneth us, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to Goſpel times, and is therefore quoted by the Apoſtle,</hi> Rom. 14. 21. <hi>with ſuch a variation of the phraſe</hi> ſwearing, <hi>into</hi> confeſſing, <hi>as plainly proves, that to ſweare by God is ſometimes a neceſſary part of our confeſſion and acknowledgment of him.</hi>
               </note> not ſwearing <hi>without any exception.</hi> For we find it frequently made a part of Gods morall Worſhip to ſweare by his name, and it is alſo joyned in the mentioned Scriptures with <hi>fearing</hi> and <hi>ſerving God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 3. Whether our Saviour Chriſt cut off by this command any neceſſary meanes of <hi>deciding controverſies</hi> between man and man, or <hi>confirming truth</hi> in matters of teſtimony? If ſo, ſurely he would thereby have rendred his Doctrine juſtly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious, as being deſtructive to humane ſociety: If not, we are certain he forbids not all ſwearing <hi>without exception:</hi> for the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> tells us that <hi>an Oath of confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is an end of all ſtrife,</hi> Heb. 6. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 4. Whether the Author in his former <hi>Article,</hi> ſetting forth God as a <hi>Pattern of perfection to us,</hi> doth not therein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us in ſome Caſes to ſweare? ſeeing we are told, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 17. that God himſelf allowes himſelf to ſweare for thoſe ends, for which an Oath is legally uſed by men, <hi>viz.</hi> for <hi>confirmation of his word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 5. Whether without ſwearing upon the call of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, all mens eſtates be not as liable to prejudice, as the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Miniſtry? And whether cheating companions will not be as prone to take the ſame advantage againſt other men, in caſe there was no judiciall Oathes required, as it ſeems (by the Authors confeſſion) <hi>Hereticks</hi> would againſt poor Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters? except we muſt take it for granted, that every mans
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118623:12"/> 
               <hi>yea, yea, and nay, nay,</hi> is as a ſufficient ſecurity in this caſe of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying the Truth judicially, as a ſolemn Oath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 6. Whether <hi>Abraham</hi> did well or ill, to require an Oath of his Servant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. 3. <hi>Jacob</hi> of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> 50. 5. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> of the Jewes, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13 25. Or (if you evade theſe examples, as being before Chriſt) whether the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did well or ill to ſweare, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, this Doctrine of the unlawfulneſſe of ſwearing in <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>14</label> any caſe, is a fragment of the old <hi>Germane Anabaptiſts,</hi> a Generation of men againſt whom the Magiſtrates ſaw ſufficient cauſe to diſpute with the Sword of Juſtice, for being publick enemies to humane Society: and it concernes you to take heed that the Magiſtracy of <hi>England</hi> may never have the like provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to follow their example againſt their genuine iſſue, the Quakers, and other Sectaries among us.</p>
            <p>But (leaſt you ſhould ſeem juſtly to charge us with <hi>ſwearing our ſelves, and teaching others to do ſo,</hi> contrary to the command of Chriſt) we muſt, in the cloſe, let you know how we ſweare, and allow others to do ſo; and what ſwearing we forbeare our ſelves, and preach downe among them, in obedience to Chriſts command: We muſt tell you, that being lawfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to witneſſe to truth upon Oath, before a Magiſtrate, we ſhall not our ſelves refuſe to ſweare, that is (according to the forme required in Law) <hi>to call God to witneſſe that we lye not:</hi> But in our <hi>communication,</hi> or ordinary diſcourſe, we deſire, both we and our hearers, may keep to our <hi>yea, yea, and nay, nay,</hi> as Chriſt commands, and <hi>not to ſweare at all,</hi> becauſe we dare not <hi>take,</hi> or allow others to <hi>take the name of God in vaine.</hi> And this we ſuppoſe to be all that our Saviour intends in that Prohibition, that <hi>in our communication we ſhould not ſweare at all.</hi> If any one be not convinced hereof by what we have ſaid, let him reconcile our Saviours Prohibition, to the precepts and examples before pleaded ſome other way, and</p>
            <p>—<hi>Phyllida ſolus habeto,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſhall gaine the cauſe in this point.</p>
            <p>Your following <hi>three Articles, viz.</hi> 6. 7, 8. are all concerning <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>18</label> 
               <hi>Tythes and forced maintenance,</hi> wherein the ſumme and upſhot of all, ſhewes your charity to the poore <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> that you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118623:12"/> would faine have them reduced to the condition of the <hi>unjuſt Steward,</hi> that is, either to <hi>work, or beg.</hi> For <hi>working,</hi> we ſuppoſe (in ſuch a Generation, as God hath now eaſt us into) we ſhall not want) whileſt beſides the ordinary attendance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our charges, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> accounted <hi>a work,</hi> and a great one too, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 12. and ſuch as none will be too forward to intrude into, that ſufficiently underſtands the weight of it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 16. The work of a <hi>Builder,</hi> a <hi>Sower,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 10. Mar. 4. 13: 1 Cor. 3. 6. 2 Tim. 2. 6. Jo. 21. 26. Heb. 13. 15. 2 Tim. 2. 3 <hi>P.</hi> 40.</note> a <hi>Planter,</hi> an <hi>Huſbandman,</hi> a <hi>Shepheard,</hi> a <hi>Watohman,</hi> a <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier:)</hi> We are called upon to anſwer every idle rayling Paper, that you, and your companions ſend us. But (ſeeing you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count this no work) it ſeemes you would have us <hi>worke with our hands, or beg:</hi> An hard Law, for men that have been bred in a way of <hi>humane Learning,</hi> which elſewhere, you ſeem to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſome uſe in the World, it may ſerve <hi>to tile the houſe,</hi> you confeſſe, and in that place you are <hi>content it ſhall ſtand.</hi> But ſurely ſhould this Law of yours take place [that thoſe that have been bred to ſtudy, muſt have no ſubſiſtence but by handy work, or begging] I feare the next Generation would yeild few <hi>Tiles</hi> to keep the houſe in repaire, ſo that it would quickly drop through, and you, as well as others, would not be able to lye dry in it: For who will give his Children ingenuous Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation at the Schooles of Learning, and ſet them there to ſpend the flower of their youth in acquiring humane literature; when the higheſt preferment they could expect after ten or twenty yeares Study, would be either to <hi>work, or beg?</hi> would not, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one conclude it better to ſet their Sons to ſome Trade or other, in their youth, that ſo at the end of ſeven yeares they might be able to get a livelyhood at their fingers ends, or turne them a begging in their Childhood, rather then maintain them twice ſeven yeares at Schoole, and Univerſity, to come thence to be preferred to a certain beggary, as being the only lot of the two, like to befall them, who are utterly to learne to work, having never been bred thereunto?</p>
            <p>But the <hi>meaſure you mete</hi> unto us, is harder yet: You that will have us work, or beg, will not allow us to carry ſo much as a <hi>Purſe</hi> to put our <hi>Wages</hi> in, when we have earned it, nor a <hi>Scrip</hi> to put our <hi>Almes</hi> in, when we have begged it; but to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118623:13"/> live as the Sparrowes do, that digeſt one meales meat in ſeeking where to get another. I ſuppoſe, ſhould God call us to that condition either by an <hi>extraordinary command,</hi> as Chriſt did his <note place="margin">Lu. 10. 7.</note> Apoſtles in the place you quote, or by an <hi>extraordinary provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> (as we ſuſpect in caſe you can compaſſe your fifth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, it would befall us) we ſhould not want faith to truſt him, who <hi>feeds the Sparrowes, and clothes the Lillies;</hi> whether in a way of <hi>working,</hi> as we are able, or <hi>asking</hi> the charity of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when diſabled: We have learned a <hi>diſtich</hi> of learned and honeſt <hi>Muſculus,</hi> which he made when the fury of the <hi>Germane</hi> Anabaptiſts (your Predeceſſors) turned him out of his Pulpit, and maintenance, and enforced him to <hi>weave</hi> and <hi>dig</hi> for a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence for himſelf and his Family.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Eſt Deus in Coelis, qui providus omnia curat,</l>
               <l>Credentes nunquam deſeruiſſe poteſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which for the ſake of your Brethren, who (whatſoever you are) are no great friends to Latine, we ſhall engliſh.</p>
            <q>
               <l>A God in Heaven lives, whoſe care extends</l>
               <l>To all, and therefore will not faile his friends.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But we queſtion yet further, whether you, that would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>19</label> us to follow preciſely the Apoſtolicall example in that Chapter, will not yet go further then this, in your rigorous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions. Suppoſe we ſhould work without a <hi>Purſe,</hi> and beg without a <hi>Scrip</hi> at your command, what ſecurity will you give us, that you will not make us work, and beg <hi>barefoot</hi> too. For if your Text concern us, we cannot ſee how we may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Shooes</hi> to our feet, more then <hi>Purſes</hi> and <hi>Scrips;</hi> and then poſſibly we might pleaſe you better, ſeeing we ſhould be more like your good friends, the <hi>Franciſcan Friers,</hi> who are the only men that we have heard of, ſince our Saviour ſent out the Apoſtles upon that extraordinary errand, who have thought themſelves concerned to walk by that rule: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you muſt have Miniſters of that character, you are moſt likely to fit your ſelves among them.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118623:13"/>
            <p>For our parts, we bleſſe God that yet provides better for us, and whileſt he continues to do ſo, we ſhall not think a profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of voluntary Monkiſh poverty, our duty to undertake, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we dare not take Gods Gifts, and throw them back into his face, by contemning the gracious allowance of his providence.</p>
            <p>As for the way of our ſubſiſtence by Tythes and forced main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>20</label> you will needs make it unlawfull as being (you ſay) a <hi>Leviticall Ordinance,</hi> and (as you add in your Book, where <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 13.</note> you againe ſerve in this <hi>Crambo) appointed as an inheritance to the Prieſts and Levites for their ſervice in the Tabernacle and Temple:</hi> and thereupon you proceed to ask theſe Quaeries in your Book.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Whether Chriſt was not the end of the Leviticall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Whether he that upholdeth that which was to have an end in Chriſt, do not deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and conſequently is Antichriſt?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Whether they that claime Prieſts and Levites Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ought not to do their work?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And this indeed is the ſumme of all that you ſay to this point; (for as <hi>to forcing the payment of maintenance by Law,</hi> it will ſtand or fall with the maintenance it ſelfe:) Concerning this we ſhall have a little debate with you.</p>
            <p>And <hi>firſt,</hi> we deſire you to underſtand, that Tithes were paid before ever the Leviticall Prieſthood was appointed. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Abrahams Victory over the Kings,</hi> and <hi>Jacobs Vow</hi> were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Leviticall Ordinances were ſet up, many hundreds of yeares.</p>
            <p>If you object (what we frequently meet withal from the men of your principles) that theſe were <hi>voluntary Acts</hi> in thoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs. However we obſerve it was lawfull to give and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them then; and it lies on you to prove when it became unlawfull.</p>
            <p>But further, we demand <hi>by what light they walked in ſo doing?</hi> was it by a <hi>Light without</hi> them, ſome traditionall rule received from their godly Anceſtors? If ſo, then it was a voluntary obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to a Law; Tradition being their Law: If by a <hi>light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them,</hi> ſome immediate motion from God ſo to do; then we
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118623:14"/> ſay; that by the ſame inward light, were thoſe Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other Proprietors of Lands that gave Tythes in this Nation, long before Popery began, moved to dedicate the Tithes of their Lands to God for ever. And ſo we receive them by the ſame Title with thoſe to whom they were then paid, excepting the conſideration of <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> as he was a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which yet confirmes our Title, as you ſhall ſee anon.</p>
            <p>And moreover we muſt tell you, that the very reaſon which God gives for his making that allowance to <hi>Levie's</hi> Poſterity afterwards, is the Title that he had to them precedent to <hi>Levi's,</hi> whence the <hi>Levites</hi> themſelves were firſt to offer them to the <note place="margin">Numb. 18. 24, 25, &amp;c.</note> Lord, and then they were to enjoy them as from God; and therefore <hi>Mal.</hi> 3 8. 9. when the people through covetouſneſſe then withdrew them, as now ſome do, God himſelf enters an <hi>Indictment</hi> againſt them: <hi>Yee have robbed me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in Tithes and Offerings;</hi> not <hi>Levi,</hi> but <hi>Me:</hi> So that they were Gods by a peculiar claime and Title, and the <hi>Levites</hi> held them from him, not from the people; and therefore they were to bring them into a <hi>Store-houſe</hi> in the Temple; as <hi>Mede</hi> a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mede on</hi> Act. 5. 34.</note> Antiquary well obſerves, and gives the reaſon from <hi>Philo</hi> the Jew, to wit, that he might thereby take away all occaſion from the people, of upbraiding the Prieſts, as if they were maintained at their charge, God firſt claiming them, and then demiſing them to the Prieſts, their maintenance became (as <hi>Philo</hi> ſaies) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>A Gift that reflected no ſhame upon the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> who thereby became Gods <hi>Eleemoſynaries,</hi> or <hi>Almeſ-men,</hi> not the Peoples.</p>
            <p>But it may be you will ſay, that the <hi>firſt claime</hi> which God <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>21</label> made to Tythes, was then, when he gave them to <hi>Levi,</hi> and ſo they were not more anciently Gods, then the other Leviticall Offerings. So that God claiming them then <hi>firſt,</hi> that he might beſtow them on the Jewiſh Prieſts, they are ſince the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Adminiſtration no more due then <hi>Sacrifices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer whereunto, we refer you to Mr. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> a man very well verſed in Jewiſh Antiquities (and one that ſhould be <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Anſw. on</hi> Gen. 14. 19.</note> more eſteemed by you being a friend to ſeparation) who tells you expreſly, that <hi>Abrahams</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> payment of Tythes was but according to their duty; as a ſigne of Tribute and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118623:14"/> to God, as Soveraign Lord and King. And <hi>Abraham</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in his payment of Tythes to <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> walked by the equity of that rule, which the Apoſtle afterwards left on record, in expreſſe termes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 27. <hi>That it was but meet, that he being made partaker of</hi> Melchizedeks <hi>spirituall things, ſhould miniſter to him in carnall things.</hi> And he further gives us ſome light to conclude that this Cuſtome of Tythe-paying, was by nature implanted in the hearts of men, or at leaſt derived by Tradition from the Patriarchs. Becauſe even the Heathens (who you ſay, have the light of Chriſt in them) paid Tythes to their Gods, which practiſe ſurely they did not take up of the Jewes (they did not love them ſo well) but from ſome higher Originall. He quotes the <hi>Athenians</hi> from <hi>Diog. Laertius,</hi> and the ancient <hi>Latines,</hi> from <hi>Pomponius Loetus,</hi> and <hi>Macrobius,</hi> for inſtances.</p>
            <p>Sir, we had not ſuffered our Pens to expatiate into this field <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>22</label> of <hi>humane Learning,</hi> but that we deale with you, who profeſſe an <hi>allowance of it in its place;</hi> and we ſuppoſe it is not out of place, in the ſearch of <hi>Antiquities,</hi> eſpecially when the queſtion is concerning the <hi>Origine,</hi> or <hi>beginning of Tythes,</hi> which you ſay (at leaſt as commanded) is <hi>in</hi> the Leviticall Prieſthood, we, <hi>before</hi> it.</p>
            <p>But we do not lay the weight of our diſpute in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>23</label> upon this foundation. We ſhall debate the queſtion with you a little more cloſely, from <hi>your own Chapter</hi> which you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to in this caſe, <hi>viz. Heb.</hi> 7. And becauſe the ſtrength of all the <hi>Quaeries</hi> thence lies in <hi>v.</hi> 12. which <hi>aſſerts a neceſſary change of the Law, upon the change of the Prieſthood from the order of</hi> Aaron, <hi>to that of</hi> Melchizedek; we deſire you <hi>firſt</hi> to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that it is not neceſſary to be granted, that by the <hi>Law</hi> there ſaid to be <hi>changed</hi> muſt be meant the Law of <hi>Tythes,</hi> but the Law of <hi>Prieſthood;</hi> that Law, that ſet up <hi>Levi's</hi> Poſterity for Prieſts, which Law differs from that of Tythes very much. However, that Scripture vvill not ſtead you vvithout interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and that you renounce.</p>
            <p>But to gratifie you, vve vvill ſuppoſe your <hi>meaning</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>24</label> for once (though that be more favour then you vvill ſhevv us:) and upon your ovvn ſuppoſition, try one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118623:15"/> with you, and that is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If the abolition of the Law of Tithes depend upon the abolition of the Prieſthood, to which they were due;</hi> then (vve hope you vvill allow us that) <hi>if the Prieſthood to which Tithes were once due</hi> (and that <hi>before the Leviticall Prieſthood) be not aboliſhed, the Law of Tithes to that Prieſthood is not aboliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But we ſhall prove that the Prieſthood to which Tithes were once due, and that long before the Leviticall Prieſthood was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is not aboliſhed,</hi> vvhich if vve do, vve hope vve may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to conclude</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore there is no aboliſhment of the Law of Tithes, but it is ſtill in force.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Prieſthood to vvhich Tithes vvere originally due is not aboliſhed, vve prove thus from the ſame Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Prieſthood to which Tithes were (before the Leviticall Prieſthood) due, was the Melchizedekian Prieſthood. But the Melchizedekian Prieſthood, or Prieſthood after the order of Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedek is not aboliſhed,</hi> For it is Chriſts Prieſthood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 16, 17, verſes. <hi>Therefore the Prieſthood to which Tithes were original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly due, is not aboliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that we ſuppoſe herein is to be proved, is, that Tithes were due to <hi>Melchizedeks</hi> order of Prieſthood, and ſo ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>25</label> due to Chriſt, vvho <hi>is a Prieſt for ever after that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for proofe of this, vve refer you higher in the ſame Chapter, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>v.</hi> 4. and thence down to the 10. And vve deſire you to conſider vvith us theſe three reaſons from the Text, to prove that <hi>Abraham</hi> paid Tithes to <hi>Melchizedek as a due.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. You pretend to skill in the <hi>Originall</hi> Tongue, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you vvill not be offended if vve argue from it, as you do more then once, or twice. <hi>Abraham</hi> (in the Apoſtles phraſe) <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 9 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> is ſaid to be <hi>Tithed</hi> by <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> and <hi>Melchizedek</hi> to <hi>tithe</hi> him, <hi>v.</hi> 6. 9. vvhich is the very ſame vvord Originally, vvith that vvhich is vſed in the Sons of <hi>Levi's tithing of the people by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, v.</hi> 5. Now if the word as applied to the <hi>Levites,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie to <hi>require Tithes,</hi> as it doth, it ſeems unlikely it was uſed vvith relation to <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> to denote a receiving of Tithes <hi>by way of gratuity</hi> only.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118623:15"/>
            <p n="2"> 2. We deſire you to conſider the ſcope of the Apoſtle in that place, vvhich is to advance <hi>Melchizedeks Priesthood,</hi> as an Order ſuperiour to <hi>Levi's.</hi> This the Apoſtle proves, becauſe <hi>Levi himſelf in</hi> Abrahams <hi>loynes paid Tithes to</hi> Melchizedek. <hi>v.</hi> 9. Now had <hi>Melchizedek</hi> received Tithes from <hi>Levi,</hi> in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> loynes, as of <hi>courteſie</hi> only, and not of <hi>debt;</hi> it would have been a poore argument to prove <hi>Melchizedek a greater Prieſt,</hi> vvhich vvill as vvell prove a Beggar a greater man then a Prince, becauſe the Beggar receives from him, it may be, a ſumm of money out of his courteſie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We deſire you to conſider that <hi>Abraham</hi> paid the Tithe to <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> with relation to his <hi>bleſſing of him,</hi> which was an act of his Prieſtly Office, and ſhewed <hi>Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dek</hi> to be <hi>Abrahams,</hi> and ſo <hi>Levi's</hi> ſuperiour, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. So that <hi>Melchizedek</hi> as a Prieſt, received tithes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and Chriſt in <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> received them from both <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Levi:</hi> which (poſſibly) may be the reaſon, why God reſerved (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven under the Law) the <hi>tenth</hi> of the <hi>Tithes,</hi> as an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or <hi>high rent</hi> to Chriſt, the Prieſt, after the order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedek,</hi> to ſhew that <hi>Levi</hi> held them of him. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18. 26, 27, 28. which tenth therefore was to be given to <hi>Aaron</hi> the high Prieſt, who was a Type of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Poſſibly you may (according to the garb of your Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>26</label> reject theſe things as our <hi>dark reaſonings.</hi> But ſeeing your owne Aſſertions and Quaeres lead us hereunto, we hope you will take them into your conſideration; at leaſt; ſo far as to ſhew us the <hi>darkneſſe</hi> of them. In a word, you may here gather our Anſwer to your three <hi>Quaeres</hi> before mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> to the</p>
            <p>Firſt; <hi>That we grant an end of the Leviticall Prieſthood in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ſecond, <hi>That in upholding Tithes, we uphold not that which was to have an end in Chriſt. Tithes being no neceſſary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant to that Prieſthood, but Chriſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the third, <hi>That we receive not Tithes upon that account, but as Miniſters of Chriſt, live upon Chriſts portion;</hi> which, till our former arguments be anſwered, <hi>we ſuppoſe Tithes to be: and therefore are not by receiving them obliged to Leviticall</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118623:16"/> 
               <hi>ſervice, but Gospell-adminiſtrations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things we have a little enlarged upon, to let you know <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>27</label> that we are not altogether ſo deſtitute of Scripture-warrant for receiving, yea, requiring Tythes, <hi>even in kind,</hi> as you (inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly enough) inſinuate us to be: Whether theſe arguments conclude the <hi>divine right</hi> of Tythes, or no, deſerves the conſideration of abler men, then you, or we, to vvhom vve humbly ſubmit our conceptions herein. However, ſuppoſing the Law of Tythes be as you ſay, Leviticall, and meerly ſo, in its originall and riſe; yet how you will prove that Law repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſo that it becomes unlawfull for any Proprietor of Land ſince that adminiſtration ceaſed, to ſet apart the ſame propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the incomes and profits thereof, for the maintenance of a Goſpell Miniſtry, vve know not; vve are ſure the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did not think the maintenance of the Leviticall Prieſthood ſo Jewiſh as you do, vvhen he makes it one of the grounds of that Goſpel-ordinance for Miniſters maintenance, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 13, 14. <hi>Do you not know, that they which Miniſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temple?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that they which preach the Gospel ſhould live of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell;</hi> and that is neither by <hi>working,</hi> nor <hi>begging.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then ſay you, this maintenance ſhould not be <hi>compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>28</label> 
               <hi>to be recovered by Law,</hi> eſpecially <hi>from the poore and needy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For the true Prophets and Ministers of Chriſt mentioned in Scripture, did not ſo live on forced ſubſtance, but ate and drank what the people gave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We anſwer (1.) That any of us ſhould force maintenance from the poore and needy by Law, we confeſſe it in <hi>matter of fact,</hi> blameworthy, becauſe in caſes of indigency, and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it is every mans duty to relax and remit a juſt debt; but in <hi>matter of right,</hi> no mans legall Title falls, becauſe of any ſuch inability. So that you muſt firſt prove, that Miniſters have no <hi>legall right</hi> to their Tenth, and then to force it from any, were ſinfull; till which, vve ſhall conceive it in it ſelf as lawfull for a Miniſter to ſue for his Tenth, as for another man to put in ſuit a juſt Bond.</p>
            <p>2. That the Miniſters of Chriſt mentioned in Scripture, did not thus, was, becauſe they had not the ſame legall right, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118623:16"/> with the power of a Chriſtian Magiſtrate: or, becauſe they were inforced to forbeare that claime among ſorbid people, who loved their Purſes better then the Goſpell, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 12. and truly ſome of us, to ſweeten perverſe Opinioniſts, are faine to remit much of our legall due to thoſe that are able to pay well enough.</p>
            <p>3. What you call <hi>forcing by Law,</hi> if you mean it of the <hi>Law of man,</hi> you condemne not us, but the <hi>publike Juſtice.</hi> If you mean it of the <hi>Law of God,</hi> you had beſt ask the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> what he meanes in the ſame verſe, by <hi>uſing,</hi> or <hi>not uſing a power</hi> of claiming maintenance from the people. <hi>If others be partakers,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of this power, Viz.</hi> Of requiring mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for teaching, <hi>are not we rather? nevertheleſſe, we have not uſed this power.</hi> And when he tells the Theſſalonians, <hi>That he might have been burthenſome to them, as the Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 6.</p>
            <p>As for your <hi>other objection</hi> againſt us, that vve do not <hi>truſt</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>29</label> 
               <hi>Gods providence, but indent for a maintenance.</hi> We anſwer, That we do not underſtand, how dependance upon <hi>divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> comes to be inconſiſtent with uſing <hi>humane.</hi> You will think it an hard caſe, if all the poore in the Country ſhould come about you, and require you to lend your Eſtate among them, <hi>hoping for nothing againe</hi> (which is as plaine Scripture <note place="margin">Luke 5. 34, 35.</note> as that you urge us vvithall in this caſe) and if you ſhould deny them ſo unreaſonable a requeſt, they ſhould tell you you are no Chriſtian, becauſe you do not <hi>truſt Gods providence;</hi> we doubt in ſuch a caſe, you would take ſhelter under ſome <hi>diſtinctions</hi> or other, as ill as you like them in the men of your ſcorne and wrath, the poore Miniſters.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>ninth Article,</hi> you excuſe your bold cenſures of our <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>30</label> hearts, in calling us <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> upon ſome <hi>pretended reaſons,</hi> as your ſelfe calls them, and vve for our parts believe them no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>In the firſt reaſon, you juſtifie the charge vvith a meer ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Viz.</hi> That vve <hi>preach againſt pride, and yet live in it, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, and yet are greedy of filthy lucre, &amp;c.</hi> Thoſe that <hi>do</hi> ſo, vve <hi>diſowne,</hi> and thoſe that <hi>do not</hi> ſo (as thouſands in this Nations do not) you <hi>belye.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:118623:17"/>
            <p>Secondly, You ſay, vve are <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> becauſe <hi>we often tell people, we ſhould have proceeded further if time had not prevented us, when as indeed we have no more to ſay.</hi> How many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have told you, they have been <hi>drawn</hi> ſo <hi>dry,</hi> that you thus charge us? It may be you did ſo vvhen you vvere a Preacher, ſo you <hi>meaſure other mens Corne by your owne Buſhell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your third reaſon is, <hi>becauſe in our prayers before Sermon, we frequently beg that he would put words into our mouthes, and teach us what to ſay, where as even then we have our Sermon-notes either in our Pockets, or our Bibles, or the platforme of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe prepared in our heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for our <hi>Sermon-notes,</hi> thoſe of us that uſe them, are faine to do ſo many times, when they vvould not, becauſe they have to do with ſuch a captious Generation as yours, vvho vvould make no conſcience of making them ſay, vvhat they do not, by miſ-reports, had they not their owne papers to juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And yet vve know not why vve may not vvrite <hi>Notes,</hi> as vvell as you write <hi>Books;</hi> vve ſuppoſe that poſterity is no leſſe beholden to ſome Miniſters Notes, then to yours.</p>
            <p>But your quarrell is not againſt <hi>Sermon-notes</hi> only, but againſt all <hi>premeditated diſcourſe.</hi> Indeed thoſe that can give themſelues liberty to <hi>talk.</hi> at the rate that your companions do, need not meditate much for vvhat they ſay; A man may ſafely ſay that heares you, that you are not guilty of premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated diſcourſes. But vve for our parts conceive <hi>Meditation</hi> a very Miniſteriall exerciſe, elſe <hi>Paul</hi> would not have required it from <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 15. Immediatly after his charge, <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>to give attendance to exhortation, doctrine,</hi> he ſubjoynes, <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on theſe things.</hi> It ſeemes the Apoſtle and you are of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall minds in this particular, as well as in point of <hi>Miniſters maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we wonder (whatſoever may be ſaid againſt thoſe that have, and uſe <hi>written-notes)</hi> how this reaſon of yours militates againſt thoſe that have only the <hi>platforme of their diſcourſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in their heads,</hi> that they muſt needs be judged <hi>Hypocrites</hi> for praying <hi>to God to put words into their mouthes.</hi> May not a man that pre-meditates his <hi>matter,</hi> ſometimes be at a loſſe for <hi>words?</hi> And may he not pray, that God would furniſh him
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118623:17"/> with expreſſions, who finds himſelf ſo, without hypocriſie?</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe that uſe <hi>Sermon-notes,</hi> might not they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe themſelves more aptly ſometimes then they write? And why then may they not pray, that God would ſupply them with apter language, upon the ſervice they are called unto, then they have prepared of themſelves? We believe there are no godly Miniſters, but find this aſſiſtance frequently, God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting their tongues to conſiderable alterations, and enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments beyond what they have before them, and bringing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to their memories, concerning which they had no actuall pre-meditation.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>tenth Article</hi> brings in an Indictment of <hi>Felony</hi> againſt <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>31</label> poore Miniſters, for <hi>quoting</hi> of the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Expoſiters</hi> of the <hi>Scripture;</hi> and this you think will juſtifie you againſt an <hi>action of ſlander,</hi> for calling us <hi>Theeves</hi> and <hi>Robbers.</hi> But we deſire you to conſider,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 1. Whether <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>Hierome,</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> be more unlawfull to be quoted by us, then <hi>Seneca,</hi> an Heathen Philoſopher, by you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 2. Whether our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> quoting <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Peter</hi> quoting <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Jude, Enoch,</hi> yea <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf quoting <hi>Aratus, Menander,</hi> and <hi>Epimenides,</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <note place="margin">Act. 17. 28 1 Cor. 15. 33. Tit. 1. 12.</note> Poets, do not as much fall under your charge of <hi>Thievery,</hi> as we, for quoting thoſe you mention?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 3. Whether a man may not <hi>receive that from the Lord,</hi> which he gathers from the <hi>writings of other men?</hi> Surely you ſuppoſe the Readers that can find leaſure enough, to look over your Pamphlet, will receive ſome light thereby. If not, why do you publiſh it? If ſo, is that light from God, or from your ſelfe, or from the Devill? We ſuppoſe you will not ſay, you write either <hi>your owne Dreames,</hi> or <hi>Satanicall ſuggeſtions.</hi> And if you ſay, <hi>from the Lord,</hi> then we hope the Lord may as well ſpeak to us, by <hi>Auſtine, Hierome, Calvin,</hi> or <hi>Luther,</hi> as by you to your Proſelites.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 4. Whether we may not as well quote the words of theſe men, and yet ſay, <hi>hearken to the word of the Lord,</hi> as you receive your principles, railings, evaſions, modes, and practiſes, from <hi>George Fox,</hi> and <hi>James Naylor?</hi> and yet cry <hi>the word of the Lord</hi> to your Proſelites?</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118623:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 5. Whether you be not your ſelves under the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, who ſuperſcribe your <hi>Quaeres</hi> (which you ſend us now and then) <hi>from the spirit of the Lord,</hi> and call them the <hi>word of the Lord to us,</hi> when we can produce the printed Books of others of your Fraternity, whence they are moſt of them ſtollen word for word. <note n="†" place="margin">T. C. <hi>his Quaeres to one of us, borrowed to a Title out of a Book</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to all that would know the way to the Kingdom, <hi>Excepting falſe eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</hi>
               </note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>32</label>
            </p>
            <p>To your eleventh <hi>Article,</hi> wherein you juſtifie your <hi>confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> in <hi>adviſing us to preach no more to the people, then the Lord hath spoken to us, and then we our ſelves witneſſe the life and power of in our ſelves.</hi> We ſay, that tis true, your are noted for <hi>confidence enough,</hi> and none more then your <hi>female Declarers,</hi> who for ſuch a <hi>ſcolding religion,</hi> as yours is, are very well furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with a <hi>Billingſgate confidence.</hi> Concerning whom (by the way) we will be bold to examine you upon a few Interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 1. Whether the Spirit of God ever did act any perſons with a <hi>boldneſſe</hi> and <hi>confidence,</hi> that breaks the Lawes of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and <hi>Civility?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 2. Whether your <hi>Propheteſſes</hi> that come to declare in publick Aſſemblies, and ſome of them ſometimes naked, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>As at</hi> Whitehall <hi>not long ſince, and elſewhere.</hi> Jer. 3. 3.</note> do not break the Lawes of Nature, and civility.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 3. Whether ſuch immodeſt practiſes, be not too great evidences againſt many of them, that they are ſo far from <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> that they have much corrupted the principles of <hi>common honeſty?</hi> And whether ſuch brazen-faced impudency in ſuch, be not in the language of Scripture, an <hi>Whores forehead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 4. Whether <hi>Pauls</hi> light or yours be better, who ſaith, <hi>Let the woman learne in ſilence with all ſubjection. But I ſuffer not a woman to teach, nor to uſurp authority over the man, but to be in ſilence,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 11. 12. Whereas you allow your women to <hi>teach</hi> in our Aſſemblies, and your owne, and in the very Streets and Market-places, and to <hi>uſurp Authority</hi> over us, who take our ſelves to be <hi>men,</hi> charging us to <hi>ſpeak no more in the name of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what <hi>confidence</hi> emboldens the reſt of you to come into our Aſſemblies, and againſt the wills of the Officers, to deliver your <hi>rayling charges</hi> there, to the diſturbance of whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, your ſelves beſt know. Only this we deſire to know of you,</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118623:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 1. Whether Chriſt, or his Apoſtles ever practiſed the like liberty, in the Synagogues of the Jewes, without leave firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from the Rulers? We find not that our Saviour Chriſt at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> opened his mouth to ſpeak to the people in the Synagogue till the Miniſter delivered him the Book, in token of the liberty granted him to teach there, <hi>Luke</hi> 4 17. 20. And we find the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and his companion <hi>Barnabas</hi> at <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,</hi> ſate down and were ſilent, till the Rulers of the Synagogue ſent unto them and gave them liberty, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 14, 15. And yet ſuppoſing they did; their miraculous gifts were a ſufficient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration that they had an higher authority. We ſee no ſuch in any of you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 2. Whether you be not herein ſo <hi>confident,</hi> as to offer vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to that very <hi>Article of the Government</hi> by which you yourſelves claime liberty; in diſturbing thoſe, who <hi>(as profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt)</hi> are worſhiping him accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Conſciences?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 3. Whether it be not an apparant deſigne of Satan, to imploy ſuch <hi>confident men and women,</hi> to make ſuch diſturbances at ſuch a time, when people ſhould go home and meditate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what they have heard, to hinder and divert them.</p>
            <p>But you think that you have warrant for all this confidence, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>33</label> becauſe you only <hi>adviſe us to preach no more to the people then the Lord hath ſpoken to us, &amp;c.</hi> Which advice of yours, were it delivered in a ſober, private, Chriſtian way, we hope we ſhould take well at your hands, and do aſſure you, that we will (to our utmoſt ability) practiſe accordingly. But we doubt, that ſo much will not ſatisfie, except we renounce what God ſpeaks to us in the <hi>written word,</hi> and hearken for Gods voice in <hi>unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten revelations.</hi> In which ſenſe, we muſt profeſſe, we think it were great <hi>boldneſſe</hi> indeed in you, to require us <hi>not to preach more then God hath ſpoken to us:</hi> Seeing you undertake to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid what God requires, and our Saviour Chriſt and his Apoſtles accordingly practiſed. The Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> tells him and us, that, <hi>the Scriptures are given by inſpiration of God, and are profitable for doctrine, reproof, correction, &amp;c.</hi> To what purpoſe is the Scripture avouched to be profitable for <hi>Doctrine,</hi> if we may raiſe no Doctrines from it? for <hi>reproof, correction, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118623:19"/> if we may not lay it as the ground of all theſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. And in the ſame Epiſtle chap. 2. 2. he commands <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>commit what he had heard of him to faithfull men, who ſhall be able to teach others alſo.</hi> Had your <hi>quaking Generation</hi> been on foot then, would they not have had the <hi>confidence</hi> to charge <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> to ſpeak nothing to the people but what he had heard from God immediatly? and thoſe that received <hi>Pauls</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine at the <hi>ſecond hand,</hi> from <hi>Timothy</hi> much more? But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> or you be to be obeyed, let ſober men judge.</p>
            <p>Sure we are that our Saviour Chriſt himſelf took for his Text, what the Lord had many years before ſpoken to the Prophet <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah, Luke</hi> 4. 17. 18. And for the Apoſtles and Apoſtolicall men, we find them preaching thoſe things which they learned from the Scriptures: <hi>Apollos, Act.</hi> 18. 28. <hi>ſhewed by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that Jeſus was the Chriſt.</hi> And when the great queſtion concerning <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the <hi>Moſaicall obſervances,</hi> was ſtarted among the <hi>Apoſtles and Elders, Act.</hi> 15. <hi>James</hi> quotes the word of the Lord to <hi>Amos, v.</hi> 16, 17. in that Aſſembly. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Act</hi> 26. before <hi>Agrippa</hi> and <hi>Feſtus</hi> profeſſeth, He in all his Doctrine, <hi>witneſſed, ſaying none other things, then thoſe which the Prophets and Moſes did ſay;</hi> So that he preached the word that was ſpoken to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and yet none that we read of, charged him to <hi>ceaſe from preaching more then God had immediatly ſpoken to him.</hi> And we hope, we may ſafely diſobey your councels or commands herein, under the protection of ſuch great examples.</p>
            <p>As for the other part of your advice to us, that <hi>we preach no more then we our ſelves witneſſe the life and power of, within our</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>34</label> 
               <hi>ſelves:</hi> We would hope you mean Orthodoxly in it; to wit, that we practiſe what we preach; w<hi rend="sup">c</hi>h if it be all you intend herein, we aſſure you we do, and we hope ſhall be enabled by grace to do ſo more and more. But when we look upon the papers of others of your brethren, we doubt you mean, we muſt not preach any thing of the <hi>Hiſtories</hi> and <hi>Propheſies</hi> of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See faith full diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of myſticall Antichriſt,</hi> pag.</note> in their <hi>literall ſenſe,</hi> but only the experiences of the Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall ſenſes their teachers faſten upon them, within our ſelves. A brief <hi>Scheme</hi> of which <hi>Allegoricall experiences,</hi> we
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118623:19"/> find in two Quakers diſcourſes, related at large by <hi>John Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervy,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Foot out of the ſnare, p.</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> out of which, that it may be known, what the Quakers your brethren would have us witneſſe in our ſelves, and then preach; we ſhall draw a ſhort Catechiſme, as faithfully, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our underſtanding we can.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 1. What is the word? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Life, or the ſubſtance whence the Scriptures are ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 2. What are the Scriptures?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>A declaration from the word of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 3. What is this ſubſtance the word of life?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>The meaſure of God manifeſted in man; the Gift of the holy Spirit manifeſted in fleſh, made known in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 4 What is the Garden of <hi>Eden?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 1. 1</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi> 5. What are the Trees of this Garden?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>All living beings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 6. Why ſo?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>Becauſe they have their being of God by ſomewhat of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that proceedeth out of the earth, God the life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 7. Where is Paradiſe?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>In man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 8. How did man fall?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>By hearkning to the weaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 9. What is that weaker?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>The fleſhly mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 10. Did not the Woman tempt him?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>Woman is that ſillieſt and weakeſt part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 11. What was <hi>Adam?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The earthly nature in man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 12. What is the Redeemer of man?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>The light by which he is given to ſee ſin, and enabled by it, if obeyed, to be redeemed from ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 13. Where is this Redeemer?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>In every particular man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi> 14. Is not that perſon the Son of God that died at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> this Redeemer?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>No.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:118623:20"/>
            <p>Theſe and the like are the Doctrines which in the ſenſe of ſome of your companions we muſt witneſſe the life and power of in our ſelves, <hi>i. e.</hi> Theſe Allegoricall experiences of the <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Scripture,</hi> as they call it, before we preach to others. Whether you be of this mind or no, we know not. But we fear you deale as partially and ſubtilly in drawing up this <hi>Article,</hi> as you do in many of the reſt, to hide the groſeneſſe of your Doctrines from the people. What followes in this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is a conſequence fancied by you, that would follow, if we ſhould herein follow your advice; <hi>Viz, That either conſtant ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or rare preaching would be found in our Congregations, &amp;c.</hi> And we think ſo too, if we have hit upon your meaning in that advice: For we have no warrant to expect immediate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations at all, much leſſe conſtantly; and leſſe warrant to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorize Scripture into ſuch odd and wretched conceits, and then preach them to the people.</p>
            <p>If your meaning be as you ſpeak, and as at firſt ſight we <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>35</label> were willing in charity to ſuppoſe, we believe your Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, would (ſhould your teachers be tyed up to the ſame Law) be in as deep ſilence as any of ours We cannot ſuppoſe that the Lord, or experience ſpeaks to moſt of you, thoſe mad doctrines of which we have given you a taſt before, and ſhall give you more anon. And we know, that there are of you that preach down pride, and yet are proud, moſt inſolently proud, moſt phariſaically proud, if Chriſt deſcribe pride aright, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 9. There are that preach down perſecution, and yet are to their power the moſt malicious Perſecuters of all that are not as themſelves; divers of you that preach down idleneſſe, and tell poore Miniſters, that <hi>if they will not worke, they muſt not eat;</hi> yet themſelves walk up and down the Land, and like lazy <hi>Lurdens,</hi> or <hi>Drones,</hi> eat the fat, and drink the ſweet at the charges of their deluded <hi>Entertainers,</hi> till (as we have had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on credible information, a ſad example lately not far from this place) they eat their Wives and Families out of doores: So that if you <hi>preach no more then you witneſſe the life and power of in your ſelves,</hi> we ſhould heare fewer declamations againſt the pride, and tythes, and perſecution of the Miniſtry, and then what would your praters do for matter to entertaine their Hearers withall?</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118623:20"/>
            <p>Your <hi>twelfth Article</hi> ſets up (plaine enough) the revelation <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>36</label> of the Spirit, in oppoſition to all <hi>humane ſtudies,</hi> but eſpecially to thoſe which are uſed in our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities.</hi> We for our parts, judge they may very well go hand in hand. We do not find but that <hi>learning and grace together, make the beſt Preachers.</hi> We do not ſay, that learning alone is ſufficient to diſcover the <hi>mind of God;</hi> but yet we believe that (if his <hi>mind</hi> be to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by his <hi>words)</hi> the underſtanding of his <hi>words,</hi> may be ſome help to the underſtanding of his <hi>mind.</hi> And ſurely, ſome parts of his mind are not to be underſtood without the help of that Learning which we call humane learning, either <hi>infuſed,</hi> or <hi>acquired.</hi> He that can underſtand <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles without <hi>Logick,</hi> divers parts of <hi>Ezekiell,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation</hi> without <hi>Mathematicks;</hi> divers peices in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> without <hi>naturall Philoſophy; Iſaiah,</hi> or the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> without <hi>Rhetorick, &amp;c.</hi> we will believe is indeed inſpir'd by God. But we conſider your Generation allow no diſcovery of the mind of God by Scriptures, and therefore it is no wonder if you will not allow any uſe of learning to draw that thence, which you will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve was ever there.</p>
            <p>But whereas you appeale to the practiſe of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>37</label> as evidence againſt the uſefulneſſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity-learning</hi> in this way. We know (for one of them) <hi>Paul</hi> he was bred <hi>at the feet of Gamaliel,</hi> and made good uſe afterwards of the great learning he got there, not only in his Epiſtles, which indeed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite the marrow of polite learning, as well as Divinity; but alſo in his diſcourſes ſometimes, as in that of his before <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa</hi> and <hi>Feſtus,</hi> which provoked <hi>Feſtus</hi> to cry out, that <hi>much Learning made him mad, Act.</hi> 26. 24. And therefore we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, we ſhall find him at leaſt indifferent in this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>And as for the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> we gather this Teſtimony from him to the uſefulneſſe of <hi>Learning,</hi> that in the very reading of <hi>Pauls Epiſtles,</hi> and other <hi>Scriptures,</hi> it may keep a man from <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 16</note> 
               <hi>wreſting them to deſtruction,</hi> which many that want it he tells us, too often do.</p>
            <p>We diſparage not the <hi>revelation of the Spirit,</hi> we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>38</label> that all the learning of the world will not bring ſaving truth effectually home to the underſtanding and conſciences of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118623:21"/> men; nay carnall reaſon back'd with learning will diſpute the light of the moſt glorious <hi>Doctrinall Truthes</hi> of the Goſpel, out of mens <hi>judgments</hi> (as is ſeen daily in the <hi>myſteries</hi> of the <hi>Perſon, natures, Incarnation, ſatisfaction, righteouſneſſe, merit, of Chriſt without us:</hi> which firſt heathen Philoſophers, &amp; Gnoſticks, and after them the Arians, Socinians, and Papiſts, and laſt of all, by the weapons borrowed from ſome, or all of them, the Familiſts, and their off-ſpring the Juſuited Quakers, or Jeſuites, and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcans under the diſguiſe of Quakers, have endeavoured to diſpute, &amp; rail out of the World) and the moſt glorious <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Truths</hi> of the Goſpel out of mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> as appeares daily in thoſe, whoſe learning Satan makes uſe of to defend and patronize their luſts: So that there needs another kind of learning to ſettle theſe Truths ſavingly in the minds and hearts of men, which the Scripture calls the <hi>revelation and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit.</hi> But yet we muſt own Learning ſanctified by the Spirit of God, as a precious help and furtherance to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Letter of the Scripture, confuting Hereticall wreſtings of them, and convincing gain-ſayers. And we won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whence all theſe that diſpute againſt Learning from the Scriptures, received thoſe Scriptures whence they diſpute, but from the help of <hi>humane Learning.</hi> Surely thoſe holy men who brought down the Scriptures to our capacities, by tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them into our Mother Tongue, were not immediatly taught the knowledge of the Originall Tongues, by the <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Spirit;</hi> but learnt it in <hi>Schooles</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> and moſt of the truths of the Goſpel which have been preſerved to us, from the violent hands of <hi>Heathen Philoſophers,</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</hi> have been very much (as to means) preſerved by the diſputes of learned men. <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate</hi> knew well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that <hi>Schools of Learning</hi> were no ſmall props of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion,</hi> and therefore when he had deſigned a totall aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtianity out of the world, he attempted it by two wayes, which your Generation unhappily follow him in, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing <hi>Schooles of literature among Chriſtians,</hi> and taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>Miniſters maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, that the <hi>Apoſtles and Miniſters of</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>39</label> 
               <hi>Chriſt in Scripture did not ſerve an Apprentiſhip in any <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118623:21"/> to learne the Trade of preaching</hi> (as you ſcornfully call it) we anſwer they needed it not, for they then received that by immediate inſpiration, which ſince that time we know no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Quaker,</hi> or <hi>other,</hi> ever attained in that way; they became Linguiſts, and Diſputants, <hi>per ſaltum,</hi> which others ſince are faine to grow unto <hi>by degrees.</hi> If you ſay the ſame Spirit dwels in you, we ſay, look you to that as to the ſanctifying and ſaving graces of that Spirit, for <hi>he that hath not the Spirit</hi> thus, <hi>is none of Chriſts, Rom.</hi> 8. 9 But as to <hi>gifts of Tongues,</hi> and other parts of learning, which were then by that Spirit, beſtowed in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant on the firſt Planters of the Church, we want an inſtance of any of you, that can ſay ſo much of himſelf. If you know any, let us heare from you in the next, who it is, and if he be able to make it out to us, we will believe him.</p>
            <p>You ſay further, that they <hi>preached but the Gospel which</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>40</label> 
               <hi>Chriſt by his Spirit revealed in them,</hi> and you quote two places of Scripture which ſpeak of revelation indeed, but not ſuch as is excluſive to humane learning, which is your drift. Indeed, in the firſt <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that God revealed thoſe things which <hi>eye had not ſeen,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to him by his holy Spirit.</hi> And in the other <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2: 10. Gal. 1. 16.</note> he ſaith, that <hi>God revealed his Son in him;</hi> but it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that in the laſt of thoſe places the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the Doctrine, much leſſe the holy Doctrine of the Goſpell that <hi>Paul</hi> preached, as if his humane learning contributed nothing to that; but only of thoſe inward operations that <hi>Paul</hi> expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced; and therefore he ſhewes the effect of the revelation, that it took him off from <hi>conſulting with fleſh and blood,</hi> which we before acknowledge as well as you.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>former</hi> of them, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſuch a revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpel, as ſavingly enabled him to receive it, feeling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to preach it, as appeareth; by <hi>v.</hi> 14. where he oppoſeth the knowledge of a <hi>naturall man,</hi> which is by meer learning, to that of a <hi>spirituall man,</hi> which is by revelation, yet not excluding learning. For by the way, you may obſerve that he doth not oppoſe a <hi>spirituall man,</hi> and a <hi>learned man [Paul</hi> himſelf was ſpirituall and learned too] but a <hi>spirituall</hi> man, and a <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> or <hi>unregenerate</hi> man, who hath nothing but naturall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and humane learning to improve them.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118623:22"/>
            <p>And (as to your aſſertion it ſelfe) that they <hi>preached onely</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>41</label> 
               <hi>that Gospel, which Chriſt by his ſpirit rovealed in them;</hi> if you mean thus, that they preached nothing but what was <hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly</hi> revealed from the Spirit without any externall help, the plaine Scripture will give you the lye. For how often did Chriſt inſtruct them, during his bodily preſence among them? And how did he expound the Scriptures to them, going through all the Bookes then penned, even from <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Malachi,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly before his Aſſention? <hi>Luke.</hi> 24. 27. So that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may be ſaid of <hi>Paul,</hi> who was called and enabled to his Apoſtleſhip in a ſingular way, untrodden by any of the reſt, we are ſure, all the reſt were taught, otherwiſe then by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate revelation of the Spirit only.</p>
            <p>But we doubt yet another Snake in the Graſſe of this faire <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>42</label> expreſſion <hi>[which Chriſt by his Spirit revealed in them</hi>] and ſuſpect it beares ſome analogy with that in your former Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, of <hi>preaching no more then we witneſſe the life and power of in our ſelves;</hi> and which you call afterwards, <hi>witneſſing the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints, whoſe words we preach,</hi> of which anon. The beſt ſenſe therefore, which comparing your words with each other, and all with the language of your other Brethren, we can pick out of your expreſſions here, is, that you ſuppoſe, <hi>they preached no more, then what by ſpirituall experience the Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in their hearts:</hi> Which if it be that you herein intend, we deſire you to conſider whether the Apoſtles did experience in <hi>themſelves</hi> the Hiſtories of the old Teſtament, which yet they preached, and whether they did experience in themſelves the <hi>reſurrection of the body, the generall judgment, and eternall damnation</hi> which they preached? Whether <hi>John</hi> experienced the <hi>Propheſies</hi> of the <hi>Revelation</hi> in himſelf, or no; as ſome of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Foot out of the ſnare, p.</hi> 6. 13.</note> you <hi>cant,</hi> that the <hi>witneſſes are ſlaine in us, and muſt be raiſed to life in us, and Babylon in us, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of this ſtamp, we doubt, is that uncouth and odd expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>witneſſing the Saints conditions</hi> (which is one of the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>43</label> phraſes we told you before, that we conceive needs interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) though poſſibly you ſpeak what you mean, yet we know not what you mean by what you ſpeak) eſpecially if we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thoſe papers which we often receive from your Diſciples
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118623:22"/> in theſe parts, with what you here ſay.</p>
            <p>But we will take you in the beſt ſenſe, and ſo to <hi>witneſſe,</hi> we ſuppoſe in your ſenſe, is, <hi>to feele by inward experience the Saints conditions, whoſe words we preach.</hi> And without this qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation (in your judgment) we muſt paſſe for <hi>Miniſters of the Letter</hi> only. We doubt you underſtand not, <hi>what a Miniſter of the Letter meanes.</hi> We are ſure, by a <hi>Miniſter of the Letter,</hi> the Apoſtle meanes not ſuch an one as <hi>expounds and applies the written Word,</hi> but either one <hi>that preached up the Jewiſh ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies</hi> according to the <hi>Letter,</hi> which were the <hi>vaile</hi> that hid the Goſpell, inſtead of Chriſt the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of them; or elſe, that <hi>preached the duties of the Law for justification,</hi> and ſo your generation are the <hi>Miniſters of the Letter,</hi> who preach up a <hi>righteouſneſſe of workes,</hi> under the notion of <hi>Chriſt in us,</hi> to the decrying and blaſpheming of the <hi>righteouſneſſe of Faith, in Chriſts perſon without us.</hi> And you your ſelfe ſpeake ſcorneful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough of it, though covertly, <hi>p.</hi> 55. of your Book, as of <hi>a righteouſneſſe beyond the Stars, and a far off from us;</hi> ſo that we feare your heart is the ſame with them, though you be more wary in your expreſſions.</p>
            <p>In a word, if we miſtake you, you muſt impute it to your darkneſſe, and ambiguity of expreſſion, which you affect in this Epiſtle, that you may (like a Carp) by running your head in the mud of uncouth and ambiguous language, avoid the Net of a juſt diſcovery and confutation: and to your undertaking, which being the juſtification of the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> we are neceſſitated to interpret you by what we know of them.</p>
            <p>To your <hi>thirteenth Article,</hi> concerning the unprofitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>44</label> of <hi>talking and profeſſing Chriſt in Orthodox notions, except we witneſſe (we will ſuppoſe you underſtand, find, and feele by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience) the life of Chriſt in us:</hi> We would hope you mean as you ſay, and no more; and if ſo, we mean and ſay as you do, <hi>that it will not availe us or our hearers to talk of Chriſts dying for us, and our being juſtified by his righteouſneſſe, except we receive a ſpirit of holineſſe from him, and be taught by the grace that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to us, to deny all ungodlineſſe, and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent world.</hi> But we <note place="margin">Tim. 2. 12.</note> muſt tell you, that we do not make our <hi>mortification of ſin, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118623:23"/> to newneſſe of life;</hi> or any of the fruits growing upon thoſe roots (though we could be as holy as ever any Saint was upon earth) any part of our righteouſneſſe in the preſence of God, but in matter of juſtification, we renounce them all as <hi>abominable and filthy rags, droſſe and dung to the righteouſneſſe which is of God by faith,</hi> and deſire to be <hi>found in him alone,</hi> who <note place="margin">Iſa. 64. 6. Phil. 3. 8, 9. Jer. 23. 5. Gal. 2. 16.</note> is <hi>the Lord our righteouſneſſe.</hi> We ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that a man is not juſtified by the workes of the Law, but by the faith of Jeſus Chriſt, even we have beleived in Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the workes of the Law.</hi> Whether you be of this judgment or no, we deſire to know more fully in your next. Thoſe of your generation are not, as we ſhall ſhew anon, from their own papers, which ſpeak out, what we ſee you have a mind to conceale.</p>
            <p>In your <hi>fourteenth Article,</hi> you confeſſe that <hi>you both publiſh</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>45</label> and <hi>practiſe,</hi> an unmannerly <hi>diſreſpect of all perſons,</hi> in which (becauſe you ſcruple ſwearing) we would (as well as we may) credit you <hi>without an Oath.</hi> And that you publiſh and practiſe it <hi>as truth,</hi> we will beleive. But <hi>Omne ſimile non eſt idem,</hi> as you may very well know. Many of your quaking doctrines (as you colour them) are very <hi>like truth.</hi> But we have in part ſhewn they are not what they ſhew for, and ſhall do more ere vve have done vvith you: Mean while vve will a little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it vvith you; <hi>Whether Religion deſtroy civility and good manners?</hi> For our parts, vve humbly conceive, that the fifth Commandement is not yet repealed, that commands us to <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our Fathers and Mothers.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> vve ſuppoſe wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by that Law vvhen he bowed to his <hi>Mother,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 29. Nor do vve dare condemne the <hi>bowing of Abraham before the Sons of Heth, Gen.</hi> 23. 7. 12. Nor do vve think that curſed <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites</hi> are more capable of civill honour and reſpect, then civill Magiſtrates. And how far the examples of <hi>Luke,</hi> dedicating his Book to the <hi>moſt excellent Theophilus, Lu.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Pauls</hi> Titles of <hi>[King Agrippa and moſt Noble Feſtus</hi>] and <note place="margin">Act. 26. 7. 25. 1 Pet. 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Sarahs calling Abraham Lord</hi> (practiſed in the <hi>old,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the <hi>new Teſtament)</hi> vvill juſtifie the practiſe of thoſe vvho beſtow Titles upon men according to their quality, from that <hi>reſpecting of perſons</hi> vvhich the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> condemnes, it <note place="margin">Jam. 5. 1.</note>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118623:23"/> may be your own ſecond thoughts will better inform you. Surely, the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> doth not deny the diſtinction of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and others in their Seates and Benches. We do not find the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> when they were called before Magiſtrates, <hi>juſtle</hi> with them for their <hi>Chaires</hi> and <hi>Cuſhions,</hi> or ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves down <hi>cheek by joule</hi> with them upon the <hi>Bench.</hi> Nor was <note place="margin">1 King. 2. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> to be charged with <hi>respecting perſons,</hi> for calling for a Chair for his Mother <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and not for all others as well that came to preſent Petitions to him. For a cloſe, we are perſwaded; that this <hi>levelling humour</hi> never laſted longer in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon, then till he himſelf got into the Chair of <hi>Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> We know no Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> that ever <hi>King'd</hi> it with that ſtate as <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> did, when he acted his part at <hi>Munſter,</hi> and yet he and his Generation were as much againſt <hi>reſpecting of perſons</hi> a while before, as any of our <hi>Quakers</hi> at this day.</p>
            <p>In a word, we are no friends to that great diſtance which meer wealth makes in the eſteem of the world between man and man, eſpecially between godly poore, and ungodly rich men. And we hope we can ſay in the ſincerity of our hearts, that we know no godly poor man whom we would not, and do not prefer in our eſteems and reſpects, as we have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to ſhew it, before any wealthy men, that are not ſo. But where the goodneſs is equall in both, we ſuppoſe the modeſty of the inferiour will not ſuffer him to be agrieved, if his Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour in any ſort ſit above him, or go before him; nor do we think it any token of humility (which is one of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent graces in true Saints) for ſuch an one to juſtle for the wall with another, to whom in common courteſie and civility, founded upon the Law of God, Nature, and Nations it is more due.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not diſpute againſt you the conſequences of this <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>46</label> your Doctrine, if it ſhould take place as they touch our ſelves. Let it follow (as you ſay) that we ſhall hereby be ſtripped of the <hi>Titles of Doctors, or Divines;</hi> we perſwade our ſelves (as <hi>well-pleaſing,</hi> as you think they are to us) we have learned of our Maſter to be contented to be <hi>made of no reputation,</hi> &amp; if God think fit to abaſe us among thoſe with whom we have to do,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118623:24"/> that vve ſhould receive as little reſpect from others, as vve do from you; vve are able through grace, to contemne thoſe poore things as dirt and dung: And if inſtead of <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Divines,</hi> vve meet vvith the Titles of <hi>Serpent, Cain, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau, Satan,</hi> yea, <hi>Belzebub</hi> himſelf (which are the honourable Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles your Generation in their great civility, or Chriſtianity af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us.) In a word, ſhould men call us <hi>Dolts</hi> inſtead of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> and <hi>Devils</hi> inſtead of <hi>Divines,</hi> we hope we can ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vanity, vve ſhould eſteem it our Crown, ſo the name of Chriſt might be exalted by the fall of our own. The <hi>Titles</hi> that men give us, vve hope ſome of us can ſay, vve procured without ambition and receive vvithout pride, and can lay down vvithout diſcontent.</p>
            <p>But vve vvonder however, how the name of <hi>Doctor,</hi> or <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>47</label> ſhould come to be ſo Apocryphall vvith you, vvho know it vvas a name of Office in the Primitive times, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11. And vvhy your brethren ſhould quarrell ſo unmercifully againſt the name <hi>Maſter,</hi> or <hi>Sir,</hi> vvhen they might know how often it is given and taken by the Apoſtles of Chriſt, who, ſurely, knew their Maſters mind in that prohibition better then they, and why (if Titles be thus unlawfull) do your ſelf give the <hi>Sirs,</hi> to your <hi>Readers,</hi> and <hi>Sir</hi> to your <hi>Antagoniſt,</hi> which is all as much as <hi>Maſter?</hi> Nay, vvhy your <hi>Son</hi> ſhould call you <hi>Father,</hi> any more then our Hearers call us <hi>Maſters,,</hi> ſeeing one Text prohibits Both, vve cannot imagine: And vve know not vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it vvas upon this account, that a Son of yours lately told one of us, that <hi>he diſowned you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But (to let this paſſe, and ſhut up this <hi>Article</hi> in a word) We ſuppoſe your other conſequence of this Doctrine vvhich you <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>48</label> mention; to vvit, the ſtripping the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> of his Titles of <hi>honourable,</hi> and <hi>worſhipfull,</hi> ſhewes ſome vvorſe blood then that that boyles in your Veines againſt the poore Miniſters. We doubt that you that vvould ſtrip them of their Titles, have no great (or it may be too great) mind to their <hi>Offices.</hi> For ſurely, there is leſſe expreſſe Authority in the new Teſtament for <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtracy</hi> it ſelfe, then for the <hi>Titles</hi> beſtowed upon them? What ſecurity then vvill you give them that you vvill not quarrell with their Robes and Maces, and afterwards with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118623:24"/> their Offices as vvell as vvith their Titles. We read of <hi>moſt excellent Theophilus, and moſt noble Feſtus,</hi> Titles as high as <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> and <hi>worſhipfull</hi> applyed to men in Magiſtracy. But of <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrates,</hi> not a vvord of Precept or practiſe; vvould you dared ſpeak out! vvhy do you nibble at <hi>Titles?</hi> tell us plainly, you ayme at the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf, moſt think you do.</p>
            <p>And now vve are arrived to the laſt of your <hi>Articles,</hi> vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you take ſome pleaſure to ſhew how you can criticize on the vvords <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou,</hi> vvhich you vvould faine juſtifie to be the only proper tearmes to any ſingle perſon A doughty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking! and very fit for your learning to mannage: We ſhould ſcarce think it vvorth the vvhile to diſpute ſuch a <hi>trifle</hi> vvith you, but only to let you know, how unfit you are to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute down <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> that mannage a <hi>Grammaticall</hi> Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo childiſhly: Should a Schoole Boy of ten years old be bid tranſlate, <hi>How do you Sir</hi> into Latine, vvould he not render it <hi>Quomodo vales tu?</hi> It ſeems your new Grammer vvould correct him vvith a <hi>Quomodo valetis vos?</hi> A learned peice of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantry!</hi> Are you ſo ſilly as not to know that Tranſlators reſpect the uſage of words in the Tongues they make uſe of: If the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators of Hebrew or Greek, had rendred <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by <hi>you,</hi> as well as <hi>thou,</hi> to a ſingle perſon, might they not have done as well to an Engliſh eare, ſeeing both words are uſed indifferently by Engliſh men? you ſhould not be ignorant of the old Rule, <hi>Loquendum ut vulgus.</hi> And <hi>Horace</hi> (if you have read him) tells you, that tis uſe <hi>(Quem penes arbitrium eſt, &amp; vis, &amp; nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma loquendi.)</hi> that words are to be regulated by.</p>
            <p>But why then do we not (ſay you) uſe the word <hi>you</hi> to the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>50</label> great God as well as to men? We anſwer, it is not neceſſary we ſhould give you any anſwer hereunto, but that you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived already. <hi>Words are proper, or improper, as uſe makes them.</hi> And yet we conceive we well vary the phraſe to God upon this account, becauſe in our prayers we addreſſe our ſelves to God in the Unity of his nature, and therefore vve uſe a word that is not capable of importing plurality, as <hi>you</hi> is. [And vvhereas you add <hi>laſtly,</hi> that <hi>the rich think it proper to ſay</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>51</label> 
               <hi>[Thou</hi>] and <hi>[Thee</hi>] <hi>to a poore man, whereas we condemne the poore man for ſaying [Thou</hi>] or <hi>[Thee</hi>] <hi>to a rich man.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:118623:25"/>
            <p>We anſwer, for our parts, we our ſelves can ſay, we know not our ſelves guilty of often making any ſuch diſtinction, and when we do, it is rather in a way of <hi>familiarity,</hi> then otherwiſe, ſeeing we have uſed in common cuſtome of ſpeech, to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the word <hi>[Thou</hi>] ſpoken to men as the more familiar word. But we inſiſt not much upon theſe things, as ſuppoſing them beneath our ſtudy or notice, but that you vvill engage us in them whether we will or no; onely we muſt tell you at parting, that you may do well (in your great acuteneſſe) to correct <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>52</label> the <hi>French Tongue,</hi> whence we ſuppoſe this manner of ſpeaking came into <hi>England,</hi> as well as our own, for the <hi>French</hi> uſe <hi>[vous</hi>] that ſignifies <hi>[you</hi>] to a ſingle perſon, as well as we. And you after that to exerciſe your pedanticall Ferule upon the royall ſtile of moſt or all the Princes in the civill World, who (with as great a <hi>Grammaticall impropriety)</hi> write in their owne perſons <hi>[Nos</hi>] and <hi>[Wee</hi>] inſtead of <hi>[Ego</hi>] and <hi>[I</hi>] vvhich is the ſtile of ordinary perſons. And vve ſuppoſe you may maintain as learned a diſpute vvith the Lord Protector about <hi>[Nos Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus</hi>] <hi>[We Oliver</hi>] as you do vvith Mr. <hi>Thomas, p.</hi> 58. of the Book about the <hi>Nominative caſe,</hi> and the <hi>Verb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are all the <hi>Articles,</hi> it ſeemes you will <hi>confeſſe</hi> againſt <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>53</label> your ſelf, and your quaking party; and becauſe you are willing to flatter your ſelf, and perſwade your Readers (eſpecially the Magiſtrate to whom this part of your Epiſtle is intended) that theſe bloody perſecutors the Miniſters, have no higher matters to charge you vvithall, you ſing <hi>Io triumphe,</hi> the day is our owne; for <hi>Theſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>are the horrid blasphemies and damnable Doctrines againſt the abettors of which you do at this day diſcharge ſo much paſſion and rage, both from Preſſe and Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit;</hi> calling <hi>upon the civill Powers for Bonds and Priſons, nay Fire and Fagot, againſt all thoſe who (fearing the Lord) do feare to call darkneſſe light, and light darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtay, <hi>Sir,</hi> we have ſome other matters then theſe to charge upon your Generation, vvhich vve vvill in the next place give you a ſhort Catalogue of, collected out of ſuch books as are either publiſhed by your ſelves, or juſtly charged upon you by thoſe Witneſſes vvho vve are aſſured vvill ſtand to their vvords vvhenever they are called to make them good.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:118623:25"/>
               <head>[The Quakers Doctrines.]</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That they are equall with God, as holy, juſt, and good, as</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>54</label> 
                  <hi>God himſelf.</hi> Affirmed by <hi>G. Fox,</hi> and <hi>J. Nayler,</hi> before Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perfect Phariſee, p.</hi> 3. <hi>See alſo the</hi> Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the irreligion of the Northern Quakers.</note> vvho atteſt it, in a Book called the <hi>perfect Phariſee,</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by five <hi>Miniſters of Newcaſtle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Suitable hereunto vvas the blaſphemy of one of your Shee-Quakers lately in hold in this Towne, vvho being convented before the <hi>Major of this Corporation,</hi> and asked what ſhe was, and <hi>what was her name,</hi> roundly anſwered (and ſtood to it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the next day) <hi>I AM THAT I AM,</hi> which will be atteſted upon Oath, by the Major and one of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Suitable to this was the blaſphemy of another of your Brethren, who meeting with a godly <hi>Londiner</hi> occaſionally being in this Town on a Lords day lately, and asking him the way, as he met him, to one of our Churches, anſwered him in theſe words, <hi>The Church is in God, and the Church is God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>That the being of God is not diſtinct from them that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by him.</hi> [Sword of the Lord by <hi>James Atkinſon</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.]</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>That the Nature and Glory of the Elect, differ not from the Nature and Glory of the Creator. For the Elect are one with the Creator in his Nature, enjoying his Glory. That the Elect is not diſtinct from the Creator. [Howgill</hi> and <hi>Burroughs</hi> two Quakers in an anſwer to <hi>Reeve.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>And that God is not diſtinct from living Creatures; for in him living (reatures lives, moves, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>That God is three perſons, or ſubſiſtences (they ſay) is a lye. That there is no diſtinctions of perſons in the Godhead.</hi> [Sword of the Lord by <hi>J. Atkinſon: G. Fox</hi> Errand to <hi>Damaſcus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>That the Soul is a part of the Divine Eſſence.</hi> [See perfect Phariſee, <hi>p.</hi> 6.]</p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt is God and man in one perſon</hi> (they ſay) <hi>is a lye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. They <hi>deny</hi> and <hi>deteſt</hi> this Doctrine, <hi>That Chriſt being the only God and man in one perſon, remaines for ever a diſtinct perſon</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:118623:26"/> 
                  <hi>from all Saints and Angels, notwithſtanding their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and communion with him.</hi> [Sword of the Lord by <hi>James Atkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>That the perſon that Son of God which died at Jeruſalem, is not the Redeemer of man from ſin; but the Redeemer is in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man, that light by which he is given to ſee him, &amp;c.</hi> [The diſcourſe of a Quaker vvith <hi>Jo: Toldervy.</hi> Foot out of the ſnare, <hi>p.</hi> 7.]</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>That Chriſt is in every man, even Heathen Indians, and in the Reprobates he is held under corruption. [J. Nayler.</hi> See per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Phariſee; <hi>p.</hi> 7</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>That Chriſt was a man, had his failings, for he diſtruſted God upon the Croſſe. [Rob. Colliſon.</hi> See <hi>Gilpins</hi> Book, <hi>p.</hi> 2.]</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>That we are not juſtified by that Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt which he in his own perſon did fulfill without us. And that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever expects to be ſaved by him that died at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: For Chriſt in the fleſh was in all, that he died and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Figure, and nothing but an example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>That we are</hi> (therefore) <hi>to be ſaved not by the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt imputed to us, but by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt inherent in us.</hi> [See both theſe in the perfect Phariſee, with their Teſtimonies, <hi>p.</hi> 9, 10, 11. And <hi>Howgill</hi> and <hi>Burroughs</hi> Anſw. to <hi>Bennet Q.</hi> 9.]</p>
               <p>And another to the ſame purpoſe ſaith, <hi>That the faith and juſtification which ſtands in the comprehenſion of Chriſt without, will ſtand us in no ſtead. [Fr. Gawler</hi> to Mr. <hi>Miller</hi> of <hi>Cardiff.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>That God and man cannot be perfectly reconciled till he be brought into the ſtate of the firſt Adam, and able in his own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſtand perfect. And that holy workes and lives of Saints are not excluded from juſtification. [Howgill,</hi> &amp;c. Anſw. to <hi>Bennets</hi> 11, 12. Quaeries.]</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>That no man that is not perfectly holy, or commits ſin, can ever enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, except there be a Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. And there is no Saint but he that is ſo perfectly holy in this life without ſin. [Nayler</hi> perfect Pharſee, <hi>p.</hi> 1. 112. 13.]</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>That to preach the impoſſibility of ſuch a freedome here on earth is to preach up ſin while the world ſtands, and to bring men into Covenant with the Diuill for term of life.</hi> [See alſo <hi>J. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118623:26"/> Shield of faith. <hi>p.</hi> 29. to both theſe <hi>Nayler</hi> in his anſwer to Mr. <hi>Baxter, p.</hi> 28.]</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>That Chriſt took not humane fleſh upon him at any time, otherwiſe then he daily doth; and that Chriſt is now converſant on earth among men ſince his aſcenſion, as he was in the Apoſtles times.</hi> It is the ſumme of <hi>Howgills</hi> and <hi>Burroughs</hi> anſwer to two Quaeres of Mr. <hi>Bennet.</hi> [See <hi>Howgill,</hi> &amp;c. in their anſwer to <hi>Benéts</hi> 18, and 19. <hi>Qu.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>That the Scriptures are not the word of God.</hi> This is their conſtant judgment though they dare not profeſſe it for feare of the Law, as one of the moſt eminent in theſe parts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed before the Magiſtrates here, in the hearing of one of us; asking <hi>Whether if the Bible were burnt, the word of God were burnt?</hi> or words fully to this purpoſe. [See the proof, Perfect Phariſee, <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>T. C. Parnells</hi> book, <hi>p.</hi> 10. ſaith, <hi>He that ſaith, the Letter is the word, is a deceiver.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="21">21. That <hi>they had a light in them ſufficient to lead them to ſalvation, if they had never ſeen or heard of the Bible.</hi> The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this was affirmed before ſome Magiſtrates of this Towne, and one of us by the ſame party. And this light exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to <hi>Heathen Indians,</hi> by him. Suitable to the aſſertions of <hi>James Nayler</hi> in a diſcourſe of his in the book quoted here. [And he that ſaith, <hi>the Letter is the rule and guide of the people of God, is without, feeding upon the Husk,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 11. See way to the Kingdome, <hi>p</hi> 8. See perfect Pariſee, <hi>p.</hi> 17. 18]</p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>That the Scriptures are not the Saints Rule of knowing God, and living unto him,</hi> but that which <hi>was before the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were written.</hi> This is alſo your owne, concerning which, anon, more at large. <hi>[Atkinſon ubi ſupra., p.</hi> 1. <hi>Parnell, p.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>That there is no need of outward teachings by reading or hearing of the Scriptures opened and applied.</hi> [See perfect Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, <hi>p</hi> 20.]</p>
               <p n="24">24. <hi>That no mens interpretations of the Scripture, or Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from them are to be received, except thoſe that give them be infallible.</hi> [See Quakers Cat. publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> where the Quaeriſts require Infallibility in a Miniſter. And Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Phariſee, <hi>p.</hi> 27.]</p>
               <p>This is generally their ſtraine. <hi>We renounce and deny all your meanings, interpretations, arguments,</hi> calling them <hi>adding to the</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:118623:27"/> 
                  <hi>Scriptures.</hi> And concerning it we muſt have a bruſh or two with you anon.</p>
               <p n="25">25. <hi>That the light in them is the Goſpell, and the more ſure word of Prophecy;</hi> ſo ſure, that ſome of them ſay, <hi>That it is a like for to take a ſentence out of their Letters, and preach from it, as to take a ſentence out of</hi> Pauls <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> [Diſcovery of myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Antichriſt diſplaying Chriſts Banners, <hi>p.</hi> 15. and 33.]</p>
               <p n="26">26. <hi>That there is no call to the Miniſtry but an immediate Call,</hi> which is generally proclaimed by them. [See perfect Phariſee, <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>J. Parnell, p</hi> 16.]</p>
               <p n="27">27. <hi>There is no Baptiſme of Chriſt, but with the H. Ghoſt and fire.</hi> And no <hi>Supper of the Lord,</hi> but in the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> part: for as for the <hi>viſible</hi> part, <hi>The bread which the world breaks is carnall and naturall.</hi> See perfect Phariſee, <hi>p.</hi> 28. and <hi>J Parnell, p.</hi> 12. 13.]</p>
               <p n="28">28. <hi>That ſinging</hi> Davids <hi>Pſalmes in Engliſh Meeter, is to ſing the Ballads of</hi> Hopkins <hi>and</hi> Sternhold King <hi>James</hi> his Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. <hi>And to ſing them is to turn the Scriptures into lyes and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies.</hi> [One of them in a Letter here at <hi>Reading. Henry Clark</hi> in his diſcription of the Prophets, <hi>p</hi> 9.]</p>
               <p n="29">29. <hi>That God made not man to be Lord over man, but over o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures; and therefore amongſt them there are no Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours after the fleſh.</hi> But are there any Superiours <hi>over</hi> them (then) that are not <hi>among them?</hi> See in the next article. <hi>[J. Parnell, p.</hi> 22, 23.]</p>
               <p n="30">30. <hi>That Chriſt comes to fulfill and end all outward Lawes and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ja. Parnell p.</hi> 18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Government of man. The righteous are from under the outward Law, for they are a Law to themſelves.</hi> Eſpecially if Magiſtrates be wicked (that is, not of them) the Author quoted in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin denies them utterly.</p>
               <p n="31">31. <hi>That there is no Sabbath now, but an everlaſting Sabbath, and that our Sabbath is but a ſhadow of which they have the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ja. Parnell p.</hi> 37.</note> 
                  <hi>And that the firſt day in the week is no Sabbath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="32">32. <hi>That we may not pray before and after Sermons, or at ſet times, daies, and houres, becauſe theſe things were in the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which were enemies to Chriſt.</hi> [Quaeres ſent to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation at <hi>Stopport,</hi> printed in a Book of Mr. <hi>Eaton.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="33">33. <hi>That the Ranters themſelves had a pure convincement which did convince them.</hi> And what their convincements were,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118623:27"/> moſt men know. To wit, that there is <hi>no Heaven, Hell, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Judgment to come; that there is no ſin, but what a man thinks to be ſo; that all that they did was done by the Eternity in them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>[G. Fox,</hi> and <hi>J. Nayler</hi> in a book called <hi>A word from the Lord,</hi> p. 13.]</p>
               <p n="34">34. <hi>That that word,</hi> 1 Jo. 1. 8. <hi>If we ſay we have no ſin we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves, was ſpoken by the carnall man. [Fr. Gawler.</hi> See Antichriſt in man by Mr. <hi>Miller</hi> of <hi>Cardiff. p.</hi> 7. <hi>Idem. ibid.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="35">35. <hi>That if a man hath ſin in him he hath none of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="36">36. <hi>They will not acknowledge that Chriſt aſcended with his body into Heaven.</hi> [Idem. ibid.]</p>
               <p>THus you ſee, <hi>Sir,</hi> how much paines we have been at to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you, that thoſe men you joyne your ſelfe unto, have matters of greater moment, then thoſe you mention, juſtly chargeable upon them: So that we are no way in feare of the judgment you pronounce againſt the <hi>Offenders of Chriſts little ones</hi> in your next lines. For if ſuch as theſe be Chriſts little Ones, we know not who are the <hi>Devills great Ones.</hi> And when you have any ſuch things juſtly to charge upon us, we ſhall not cry out of hard meaſure, although we ſuffer more then any of you yet do. Let the Magiſtrate <hi>do ſo to us, and more alſo,</hi> if we thus deſerve it.</p>
               <p>As to what we lay to your charge, whether he will take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it or no, we have learned not to be over ſollicitous, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are not out of hope that <hi>deliverance will ariſe</hi> for Gods reproached Miniſters, Truths and Ordinances, ſome way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And yet we cannot but deſire he would vouchſafe this honour to thoſe that are now in Authority over us, <hi>that Truth and peace might flouriſh together in our daies under their wings.</hi> And truly, <hi>Sir,</hi> did you know our hearts (whatſoever Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of perſecution and blood you judge us to be) you would ſee, that as it is no private intereſt of our own, that drawes us out to appeare againſt you, but the meer concernments of Gods Glory, and precious Truth; ſo we deſire nothing more then the conviction and reduction of you, in a Goſpel-way. And this we can clearly ſay, that of all thoſe that have ſuffered any thing, in, or neer the places where we live, we know none
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118623:28"/> of them, but have drawn it upon themſelves, by firſt making ſuch publick diſturbances, as brought them within the reach of the Law, and then refuſing to give bayle, out of a fond ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they had to be impriſoned, when they might have avoided it.</p>
               <p>And yet we cannot but wonder, how an handfull of you, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>55</label> bidding defiance to whatever of publick Religion is profeſſed in this Nation, ſhould think, or with any reaſon expect to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected in the diſturbance of all others, who, as the preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of affaires ſtands, are under an equall liberty with your ſelves; and if you be denied to perſecute all others, or by proceſſe of Law reſtrained from it, complaine of perſecution. So that indeed, if the Magiſtrate grant you ſuch a protection, walking by the principles you do, he denies it to all elſe; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſociety of Chriſtians whatſoever would enjoy the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of their Worſhip, without diſtraction from you. And to perſwade the Magiſtrates to give you liberty of tearing up all the profeſſed Religion in <hi>England,</hi> and blaſpheming it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly where ever you come, we ſuppoſe it will in reaſon be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that you ſhew ſome extraordinary Authority or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God, teſtified by ſome reall ſigne to convince them that it is not counterfeit; and yet even then, as you ſhall ſee anon (your Doctrines being ſuch as they are) they may ſee juſt cauſe to lay ſome reſtraint upon you therein.</p>
               <p>In the mean while, we muſt tell you, that however you may pleaſe your ſelves in your ſufferings, and vent your paſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the men from whom you conceive they ariſe, as ſo many <hi>Sauls</hi> and <hi>bloody Perſecuters,</hi> yet God judgeth not Martyrs by the <hi>ſuffering,</hi> but the <hi>cauſe;</hi> and you had need examine in whoſe <hi>Errand</hi> you go, when you run your ſelves upon <hi>ſuffering,</hi> as well as others to examine upon what <hi>Warrant</hi> they inflict it upon you. If every one be a <hi>Martyr,</hi> who makes a loud cry of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> ſurely the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> will not be behind hand, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in for his ſhare, as well as you; and if every one be a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor</hi> that curbs and reſtraines unruly and diſorderly Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, wo be to thoſe <hi>Judges</hi> who arraigne, and condemne <hi>Fauxes</hi> and <hi>Ravilliac's,</hi> who plead conſcience for what they do, as well as your ſelves. The truth is, both you, and we, and all
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118623:28"/> perſons, muſt be able to plead, that we ſuffer not as evill doers, and then ſuffering will be a comfort and a crown; otherwiſe what we ſuffer we ſuffer in our owne wrong, and ſhall when we have ſuffered our Eſtates out of our Purſes, and Soules out of our bodies, meet with no other entertainment, then an <hi>Who hath required theſe things at your hands?</hi> And we deſire you particularly to conſider what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells you, that if a man <hi>give up his very body to be burned, and have not charity,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>it profits him nothing:</hi> And ſurely if your generation be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, you are the moſt uncharitable ſufferers that ever were; and Martyrs, that have been in the World, from Chriſts time till the ſtarting up of your new Apoſtles, within theſe 3. or 4. years; &amp; are ſo far from that charity w<hi rend="sup">c</hi>h other ſufferers in Scripture have had to their bloodieſt Perſecutors, that your mouthes are full of rayling, reviling, curſing, and bitterneſſe, to thoſe that do not meddle with you further then it concernes them in their places, to preſerve others under their charge from the infection of ſuch abominations as thoſe fore-mentioned. However <hi>We have not ſo learned Chriſt,</hi> as to <hi>render evill for evill,</hi> but deſire to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer under the ſharp Arrowes of your tongues, as he gave us an example, not reviling againe when we are reviled by you, but <hi>committing our Cauſe, Callings,</hi> and <hi>Maintenance to him that judgeth uprightly.</hi> And to <hi>inſtruct</hi> even the worſt of <hi>Oppoſers in meekneſſe, trying if God will at any time give them repentance, to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 25. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>the acknowledgment of the Truth; and that they may recover them out of the ſnare of the Devill, who are taken captive by him at his will,</hi> which we yet (with pity towards, and prayer for you) are aſſured to be the condition of your ſelfe, and your Clients in this Cauſe.</p>
               <p>ANd now, <hi>Sir,</hi> after a tedious purſuit of you, through all <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>57</label> the windings and turnings of your ſubtle inſinuating Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, it may be expected we ſhould proceed to your Book it ſelfe; But we ſhall wave it, as we before told you, for theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe a great part of it hath been once <hi>ſerved up</hi> in the Epiſtle, and becauſe we found it not ſeaſoned with ſalt, by
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118623:29"/> us already diſcovered and rejected as unſavoury. So that we ſhall not cloy the Reader with a <hi>ſecond courſe</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe that we find that it is wholly made up of perſonall conteſts with Mr <hi>Thomas,</hi> and inſolent reflexions and reproaches upon him, into whoſe harveſt we deſire not to thruſt in our Sicle; beſides that we are advertiſed, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to take that task in hand himſelfe, and we are aſſured that he will not need any aſſiſtance from us, or any other, to anſwer it as it deſerves. Onely becauſe you ſo often call the Scriptures (in ſcorne) <hi>[our Rule</hi>] in your Epiſtle, and therein expreſly reject <hi>all Interpretations and deductions</hi> which we draw from them in preaching, or diſpute; we will here ſubjoyne theſe two queſtions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 1. <hi>Whether the holy Scriptures be the Saints ground, and rule of faith, and practiſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 2. <hi>Whether it be lawfull without an infallible ſpirit, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret Scripture, or draw conſequences and deductions thence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In both theſe you defend the <hi>Negative,</hi> we the <hi>Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the firſt of them in your Book, you ſtand only upon <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>58</label> your defence againſt ſome Texts quoted by Mr. <hi>Thomas;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which we leave you to his ſecond charge, wherein we doubt not but he will <hi>fetch them off</hi> without loſſe. Mean while, we cannot but take notice of the Artifices of your ſelfe, and others of the generation you cloſe withall.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) We obſerve, that in moſt or all matters of difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, you put us upon the proof of <hi>our</hi> Principles and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and offer none for your <hi>owne;</hi> which is a ſlye way of <hi>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> your owne <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> and <hi>diſcovering</hi> our <hi>ſtrength,</hi> that ſo you may make your advantages of it: Which is, as if a man ſhould ſue another at Law, to produce his evidences by which he holds his Land, to be canvaſſed by his owne Counſell, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exhibiting any thing in his owne behalfe, to juſtifie his claime to it.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) We obſerve alſo, that you reſerve to your ſelves a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of excepting againſt the <hi>Juriſdiction of the Court,</hi> in which the cauſe is depending; not allowing it a power to decide the caſe, if you ſee you ſelves likely to be caſt in Judgment, although
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118623:29"/> you will owne it ſo far as you ſuppoſe it may ſerve your turne againſt us. For you call us forth to a tryall by the Scriptures, and yet will not allow them to be the rule to decide the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) We obſerve thirdly, that you will have the choice of the <hi>Weapons</hi> in this encounter, not only for your <hi>ſelfe,</hi> but <hi>us</hi> alſo, ſetting up a <hi>Star-chamber Court</hi> of your own firſt, to damne our Evidences, and then, forſooth, you will fight with us when you have diſarmed us. You will diſpute with us from the Scripture, and yet will allow us no Arguments to diſpute withall. A valiant undertaking, and worthy peice of Chival<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for which you deſerve to be recorded among the chiefe Champions of the <hi>Quaking Knight Errantry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we hope, upon ſecond thoughts, you may be perſwaded <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>59</label> not to diſparage your owne atchievements upon us, by keeping your ſelfe within the ſecurity of an <hi>Iriſh bogg,</hi> where it is harder to <hi>come</hi> at you, then <hi>conquer</hi> you, and come forth into the plain field, where we may encounter you upon even termes. If o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, we ſhall take it as an Argument of your Cowardize, and yet rather ſwallow any inconvenience, then not <hi>diſlodge</hi> you, and ſet up the Banners of Truth upon your owne ground.</p>
               <p>And <hi>firſt</hi> we will try you with a few <hi>Quaeries,</hi> which (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>60</label> they are your owne familiar way of arguing) we hope you will admit into your conſideration.</p>
               <p>Q. 1. <hi>Whether you will receive the Scriptures Teſtimony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it ſelfe, or no?</hi> If you will, then Q. 2. <hi>Is it not the rule of faith by your owne confeſſion?</hi> For it is that to which you ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſaith in this queſtion. If you will not, then Q. 3. <hi>To what purpoſe do you require of Mr.</hi> Thomas <hi>to produce a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſaith,</hi> in Terminis, <hi>it is the rule;</hi> when if he do, the queſtion is as far from being decided as before?</p>
               <p>In the next place, we will ſtate the queſtion between us, that <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>61</label> we may underſtand one another.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore the queſtion betwen us is not, <hi>Whether the Scriptures, or written word, have been the ground and rule of faith and practiſe, in all ages of the World,</hi> but <hi>whether in every age of the World, ſince any part of them was written, ſo much as was written in any age, were not the rule by which thoſe of that age</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:118623:30"/> 
                  <hi>were to be regulated?</hi> and conſequently, <hi>whether to the ages that have been, and ſhall be, ſince the whole was compleated, the whole be not ſo, and to continue ſo to the Worlds end?</hi> So that you are quite beſides the <hi>Cuſhion</hi> and the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> in the inſtances of <hi>Abel, Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Ahraham,</hi> and all the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> before <hi>Moſes,</hi> who wrote the firſt Scripture. We are not ſo ſilly as to affirme the <hi>word as written,</hi> to have been a <hi>rule before it was written.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we ſhall not doubt to prove, that thoſe Patriarchs had the ſame <hi>foundation</hi> to <hi>build</hi> on, and the ſame <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Rule</hi> to <hi>walk</hi> by, though they were not then committed to <hi>writing.</hi> The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 8. that the <hi>Scripture preached the Gospel to Abraham;</hi> where it is obſervable, <hi>that</hi> Abrahams <hi>light was Scripture light, before the Scriptures were written.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. The queſtion between us, is not, whether the Scriptures be the <hi>perſonall</hi> or <hi>reall</hi> ground of faith; but whether (as Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> well diſtinguiſheth) it be the <hi>Doctrinall</hi> or <hi>declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> ground, or foundation of faith? This diſtinction, whether you will admit or no, we muſt premiſe, becauſe we would not be engaged to fight with a meer ſhadow. If you will own the Scriptures to be a <hi>doctrinall foundation or ground of faith, i. e.</hi> to hold forth from God thoſe Doctrines, which, and which onely we are bound to beleive, our diſpute is at an end, for we are of a mind; we owne <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone to be the foundation or ground of faith, <hi>perſonall</hi> or <hi>reall;</hi> that is, to be the <hi>perſon,</hi> or <hi>thing,</hi> that our faith is built on; and the Scriptures to be the onely ground and foundation, by way of Doctrine or declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>what</hi> we are to beleive concerning Chriſt, and <hi>how</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive on him. We hope you will underſtand us, we ſpeak as plaine as we can to avoid cavills about termes.</p>
               <p>All therefore that we are to prove in this queſtion is, that all things which vve beleive and do, as neceſſary in order to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are to be ſuch as are contained in the Scripture, and to be judged by it, whether they be ſo or no.</p>
               <p>We ſay, <hi>All things which we beleive and do as neceſſary in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>62</label> 
                  <hi>to the ſalvation of our Soules, are to be ſuch as are contained in Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If not (becauſe to pleaſe you, we muſt not <hi>argue</hi> from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) we deſire you to ſatisfie us.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:118623:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 1. <hi>What thing neceſſary to be beleived or done, in order to ſalvation there is, which we may or muſt receive from any other Rule, or build on any other foundation, and what is that Rule or foundation.</hi> We ſuppoſe you are bound either to allow <hi>our</hi> rule, or ſhew us a <hi>bettor.</hi> Or,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 2. <hi>Whether what the Scriptures containe, be ſufficient to guide us to ſalvation, or no?</hi> If you <hi>affirme</hi> it; then we ſhall think our ſelves well enough with our <hi>old Rule,</hi> ſeeing vve may be ſaved, and yet admit no other.</p>
               <p>If you deny it, you muſt out-ſtare theſe plaine Texts, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15, 16, 17. <hi>From a Child thou hast knowne the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which are able to make thee wiſe unto ſalvation.</hi> And <hi>all Scripture is given by inspiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. That the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto every good work.</hi> And that of <hi>John,</hi> wherewith he cloſeth his twentieth Chapter. <hi>Theſe</hi> (ſpeaking of the ſignes which Chriſt did) <hi>are written, that yee might beleive that Jeſus is the Chriſt the Son of God, and that beleiving, yee might have life through his name.</hi> Say not, that this concernes onely the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of <hi>John,</hi> or if more, onely the Hiſtories of the Evangeliſts. For then we ſhall make bold to conclude our Poſition <hi>à fortiori.</hi> If there be enough in <hi>one,</hi> or at moſt <hi>four</hi> Bookes to work faith, and thereby <hi>bring</hi> us to ſalvation, much more in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 3. <hi>Whether the Scriptures of the old and new Teſtament be the word of God, or no? or do you owne no word of God, but Chriſt?</hi> We ſuppoſe here you will anſwer us, as your brethren here do: We dare not deny it for feare of the Law; we dare not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it, for then we deny our own principles.</p>
               <p>We know not how you will anſwer it: But we muſt tell you, if you <hi>deny</hi> it, we are ſure the Scriptures affirme it of <hi>themſelves;</hi> elſe we deſire to know, what it is that is called the <hi>Word of God</hi> in the places following <hi>Mar.</hi> 7. 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 17. 4. 2. What it is that <hi>David</hi> ſo often calls by the name of <hi>thy word, Pſ.</hi> 119. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt ſpake <hi>himſelfe,</hi> or the <hi>declarative</hi> word of God, <hi>Lu.</hi> 5. 1. If you <hi>affirme</hi> it, We ask further;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 4. Whether it be not the duty of the Creature to beleive
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118623:31"/> and be guided by the declared word of God, rather then by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others word whatſoever?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 5. Whether there be any ſuch thing in the World as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie,</hi> or <hi>Errour?</hi> If there <hi>be not,</hi> to vvhat purpoſe are all thoſe Propheſies that foretell, and Cautions that forewarne Gods people againſt them in the Scripture? If there <hi>be,</hi> may they <hi>be diſcovered,</hi> or <hi>no?</hi> If they may <hi>not,</hi> how can it be a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon Saints to avoid them? is there any avoiding of an undiſcoverable evill? If they <hi>may,</hi> by vvhat rule but the written Word?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 6. Whether there be any <hi>duty,</hi> or <hi>ſin</hi> in the World, or no? The affinity your Sect hath vvith the <hi>Ranters</hi> in Principles (vvhich <hi>G. Fox</hi> acknowledgeth) makes us beleive, that ſome of you, vvould they ſpeak out, muſt anſwer, <hi>No, but what a man thinkes to be ſo.</hi> We vvill not judge the thoughts: But if you be more ſober, vve onely ask you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 7. What rule vve have to judge of vvhat is Duty, or Sin, but the vvritten Law of God?</p>
               <p>Is it the <hi>light</hi> of every mans <hi>private boſome?</hi> This is the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Ranting Principle.</p>
               <p>Is it immediate Revelation? For to this your brethren in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline (as may be ſeen in the <hi>Quaeries</hi> ſent to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> of <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminſter,</hi> one of vvhich vvas, <hi>Whether he owned Revelations, or no?</hi> And <hi>Naylers</hi> Anſwer to his <hi>Quakers Catechiſme)</hi> and that very ſtrongly; yea, they pretend to the ſame miſſion from God to this or that place, to do this or that errand, which the Prophets had of old, and to be limited in their ſtay in, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from ſuch places, by the immediate commands of God <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Deuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, <hi>and his owne confeſſion therein, That at</hi> Derby <hi>he anſwered the</hi> Major, <hi>that</hi> he would ſtay there till the Lord ordered him to go out of Towne, <hi>and when he was put out, returned, and</hi> ſtaid till he was free in his ſpirit to depart, <hi>p.</hi> 8, 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If you be of their mind, vve further enquire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 8. What certaine token you have to know the <hi>commands of God</hi> from the <hi>commands of Satan,</hi> ſeeing he can eaſily inſinuate his ſuggeſtions by inward voices, as commands of God. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>old</hi> Law of God to his people the Jewes, Pretenders
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118623:31"/> to a Spirit of Propheſie, though they gave evidence of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended miſſion from God by <hi>ſignes and wonders</hi> (and thoſe coming to paſſe too) yet were to be diſcovered and judged by the <hi>written word, Deut.</hi> 13. 1, 2, 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Doctrine of an <hi>Angell from Heaven</hi> is ſubmitted (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a curſe) to the Doctrine preached by the Apoſtles, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8. And we deſire to know whether you vvill ſubmit your Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to this Touchſtone, or no? If <hi>ſo,</hi> you yeild the queſtion: If <hi>not,</hi> then whatever Commands or Prohibitions you receive in the way of revelation, you muſt obey, vvhether agreeing, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing to the written Law of God. And then how far the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Abraham offering up his Son, and Phinehas executing vengeance;</hi> yea (and vvhen time ſerves) <hi>Ehuds meſſage from God to Eglon,</hi> may be <hi>witneſſed in you</hi> (as you ſpeak) we know <note place="margin">Judg. 3. 19</note> not, and ſhall pray vve never may, by experience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 9. Whether the Scriptures do not eſtabliſh it ſelfe as the rule of <hi>Faith,</hi> in referring all pretenders to <hi>new light,</hi> to the <hi>Law and the Teſtimony,</hi> and telling us expreſly, <hi>That if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 20. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>them.</hi> And whether the light in you and in your companions be not darkneſſe, that will not undergo this tryall?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 10. Whether the phraſes of <hi>walking in the Law of the Lord, keeping Gods Teſtimonies, taking heed to a mans, way ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods word, not wandering from Gods Commandements,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 119, 1, 2. 9, 10. 21. 30. 35. 51. 102. 110. 133. 157.</note> 
                  <hi>laying Gods Jugdments before him, going in the path of Gods Commandements, not declining from Gods Law, not departing from Gods Judgments, not erring from his Precepts, ordering his ſteps in Gods word, not declining from his teſtimonies;</hi> Are not cleare evidences, that <hi>David</hi> made the written word that then was, his Rule? And you owne <hi>Davids Rule</hi> for yours, <hi>p.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 11. Whether you think in your conſcience, that <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 32, 33. doth not convincingly prove the Scripture to be the Saints rule? The words are, <hi>Yee ſhall obſerve to do therfore, as the Lord your God hath commanded you</hi> (and before vve have the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitition of the written Law) <hi>You ſhall not turn aſide to the right hand or to the left,</hi> &amp;c. Your anſwer in your book, is in ſumme, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 7.</note> that <hi>all the Scripture was not then written.</hi> But did not <hi>Moſes</hi> therein eſtabliſh <hi>as much as was then written,</hi> for the rule the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118623:32"/> Saints of thoſe times were to walk by. Beſides theſe words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly refer to the <hi>Morall Law,</hi> before repeated in the ſame Chapter. And will you exclude that from being the Saints rule, as well as other Scriptures? Then indeed there vvill be <hi>no duty or ſin, but as a man thinks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 12. Whether you deale honeſtly with <hi>Calvin</hi> in that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 20.</note> Scripture, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 20. whileſt you tell your Readers that he ſaith <hi>in Terminis, That the Apoſtle doth in that Scripture intend Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to whom the Prophets and Apoſtles did beare witneſſe.</hi> Whereas <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith expreſly, <hi>It is without doubt that the [foundation</hi>] <hi>in this place is taken for the [Doctrine</hi>] <hi>of the Prophets and Apoſtles. And therefore</hi> Paul <hi>teacheth, that the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quin fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentum hic pro do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me dubium eſt. Et ita<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> docet Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, fidem eccleſiae, in hac doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na debere eſse funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam Calv. in l.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Churches faith ought to be founded on this Doctrine.</hi> And there is not any mention at all of thoſe vvords in <hi>Calvin,</hi> vvhich you quote from him. To ſay the truth, vve much vvonder how you could have the brazen face to father a ſaying upon <hi>Calvin</hi> vvhich he never ſaid: till vve looked upon <hi>Marlorate,</hi> whoſe miſ-quotation, or rather the fault of his Printer (it ſeemes) deceived you, for there vve find among other things there aſcribed to <hi>Calvin,</hi> this paſſage you mention. But it concerned a man of your acuteneſſe, not to have taken up a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port from another, vvhen <hi>Calvins</hi> vvorks are ſo common in every Shop and Study, that vvith a little paines more, you might have converſed vvith the Originall Author, whence <hi>Marlorate</hi> makes his collections. But it ſeemes you vvere vvilling to ſnatch at any thing that ſeemed to ſupport your cauſe, vvhere ever you found it. And yet you ſhewed no part of ingenuity in your uſage of <hi>Marlorate</hi> himſelf, vvho together vvith that paſſage vvhich you quote, and under the ſame note by which he diſtinguiſheth <hi>Calvins</hi> vvords, cites <hi>Calvin</hi> point blank againſt you, ſaying, that the Apoſtle ſhewes in that place how the <hi>Epheſians</hi> vvere made fellow Citizens vvith the Saints, <hi>Nempe ſi fundati ſint in Prophetarum &amp; Apoſtolorum Doctrinâ,</hi> to wit, <hi>If they be founded on the Doctrine of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words and others to the ſame purpoſe immediatly precede your owne quotation, vvhich renders your diſ-ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the more culpable, as ſhewing a vvilfull deſigne of abuſing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118623:32"/> ſo reverend a name to delude your Readers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 13. In a vvord, tell us ingenuouſly, <hi>Whether we muſt, or muſt not beleive the Doctrines which the Scriptures lay downe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their owne authority?</hi> If vve <hi>muſt,</hi> vvhy do you quarrell at thoſe that call them the <hi>rule, ground, foundation of faith;</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every intelligent man will tell you, that it is the ſame thing, <hi>to beleive the Doctrines of the Scripture upon the Scriptures au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> and to <hi>make the Scriptures the ground, rule, foundation of faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If vve <hi>muſt not,</hi> then tell us, what, ſuperadded to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures owne Authority, renders their Doctrines more credible? We obſerve the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſtate this queſtion as you do. But they vvill anſwer us ingenuouſly, <hi>That they beleive the Scriptures, becauſe the Church hath confirmed them.</hi> And the <hi>Socinians</hi> are of your mind alſo; but they deale <hi>fairely</hi> too, and ſpeak out, <hi>That they will beleive the Scriptures as far as reaſon votes with them.</hi> Would you ſpeak out, vve doubt you muſt confeſſe you are very neer theſe laſt in your judgment: Why do you not tell us plainly; <hi>that you beleive the Doctrines laid down in the Scripture, as far as the light within you concurs with them?</hi> And then vve ſhall know vvhat you mean, in denying the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be the <hi>rule and ground of faith, Viz.</hi> That as much as pleaſeth you you vvill beleive, and vvhat diſlikes you, ſhall be caſhiered as an <hi>old Declarative,</hi> or an <hi>Almanack out of date,</hi> as ſome of your Cater-coſins, the <hi>Familiſts</hi> have blaſphemouſly called the Bible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 14. Laſtly, Whether God vvill not judge every man, vvho lives within the ſound of the Goſpell, by the <hi>written word?</hi> If <hi>not,</hi> what meanes the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaith, that <hi>as many as have ſinned in the Law, ſhall be judged by the Law, in the day when God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Gospel,</hi> Rom. 2. 12. 16.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing we are upon this ſubject, give us leave to enquire yet a little further; what are thoſe Books out of which the dead ſhall be judged, and whence one day God will draw the rule of his proceedings in the day of Judgment, as you may find, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
               <p>If God vvill judge us out of the written word after death,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118623:33"/> ſurely, we are not to be blamed, if we ſtudy that Statute-Law, and labour to conforme our beleif, and practiſe thereunto whileſt we live, which muſt judge us when we dye. Or elſe, we pray you tell us, whether we muſt <hi>live</hi> by <hi>one</hi> rule here, and be <hi>judged</hi> hereafter by another?</p>
               <p>In your anſwer to theſe <hi>Quaeries,</hi> we muſt deſire you not to play <hi>Childs play</hi> with us, and endeavour to put us off with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling <hi>fallacies,</hi> which every <hi>Sophiſter</hi> can diſcerne, as you do frequently in your particular conteſts with Mr. <hi>Thomas,</hi> which we doubt not you will here of with both eares, when he is at leaſure to reply upon you: but deale candidly and poſitively as becomes a <hi>Scholar,</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> with thoſe who aſſure you they will with all poſſible faireneſſe examine whatſoever of that nature you ſhall think neceſſary to rejoyne hereunto.</p>
               <p>And here we ſhall put a period to our <hi>firſt debate</hi> with you, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>63</label> concerning the <hi>Rule, ground, or foundation of faith:</hi> Which we ſay is the Scriptures, you (that we can find) yet ſay not, what it is, but say roundly it is not they.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>next</hi> friendly collation is about the <hi>way of drawing thoſe Doctrines from the Scripture,</hi> which are to be beleived and practiſed. Concerning which, your declared judgment is (as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 5, 6. 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> well as vve can gather it from your own expreſſions) <hi>That it is unlawfull to interpret, or give any meaning of Scripture, or to draw any deductions and concluſions from it; but that we muſt reſt ſatisfied with the bare words of Scripture,</hi> inſomuch that nothing (according to you) is proved from the Scripture, but what is there in <hi>ſo many words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning vvhich <hi>Tenet</hi> vve have a little <hi>knockt Shins</hi> with you before <hi>at armes end,</hi> but vve ſhall now <hi>wreſtle a faire fall,</hi> and come as cloſe as we can, to give you a down-right <hi>Corniſh hugg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> therefore we muſt informe you, that <hi>your Generation</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>64</label> are not the firſt that have ſtarted the queſtion, or ſo held it. We know not vvhether you underſtand <hi>French,</hi> or no, but if you do, vve refer you to a diſcourſe of Mr. <hi>Daillé,</hi> as learned a French man as any this latter age hath bred; who in a Book <note place="margin">Lafoy fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee ſur les S. Eſcritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, par Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Daille.</note> printed about ſixteen yeares ſince, hath a large diſpute vvith certaine <hi>Popiſh Methodiſts,</hi> vvho undertook to teach their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:118623:33"/> Proſelites, the ſame way of confuting the <hi>French Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> which you now principle your Diſciples withall, to gravell thoſe of this Nation. <hi>They deem</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that there needs no more ado to baffle us, but to demand of us an expreſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Text for every Article of our confeſſion. This facile way</hi> (ſaith he further) <hi>hath produced a rabble of Disputants among them: and whereas at firſt they fled and declined all conferences of Religion, and permitted none but their Clergy to ſpeak of it; now all ſorts of people will adventure to engage with us, even Seamſters, and Carters Boyes, being created Doctors in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant by this handſome Method.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>ſame Author</hi> derives the riſe of it higher then that age too: But from ſuch a <hi>Family,</hi> as neither they nor you have much cauſe to boaſt of. <hi>Eutiches</hi> the Heretick, that confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Natures of <hi>God</hi> and man in the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſ. Ep. de Synod. Arim. &amp; Seleuc.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Et Dialog cont. Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Aug. Ep.</hi> 174. <hi>&amp;</hi> 178. <hi>Id. Contra maxim? T.</hi> 6. <hi>fol.</hi> 144. <hi>G.</hi>
                  </note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired an <hi>expreſſe Scripture</hi> to affirm, that <hi>in Chriſt there are two Natures.</hi> The <hi>Arians</hi> in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his time and after, denied the <hi>conſubſtantiality</hi> of the Son of God; <hi>Viz. That he was of the ſame ſubstance with the Father</hi> (aſſerted by the Councill of <hi>Nice,</hi> to expreſs the <hi>Eternall Deity</hi> of the Son) as you do the word <hi>Sacrament,</hi> becauſe it is not in ſo many Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters found in the Scripture. And concerning the very <hi>Godhead</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in a Dialogue between <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, Let alone Syllogiſmes, ſaith the Arian,</hi> and <hi>ſhew it us written that the Son is the true God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Paſcentius</hi> an <hi>Arian</hi> requires of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to ſhew him the word <hi>conſubſtantiall</hi> in Scripture, <hi>without Argument.</hi> And in a like diſpute between him and <hi>Maximinus,</hi> concerning the <hi>Godhead</hi> of the <hi>H. Ghoſt,</hi> when the <hi>Father</hi> proved it from the Scripture, that tels us, <hi>He hath a Temple,</hi> the proper adjunct of <hi>Divinity;</hi> the Heretick replies, <hi>Truth is not concluded by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but proved by certaine Teſtimonies.</hi> Theſe things we have the more largely tranſcribed out of that <hi>learned Author,</hi> to let you know, out of what <hi>Forge</hi> that Weapon is hammered wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you encounter us. Follow you now (if you pleaſe) the <hi>ancient Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>moderne Papiſts.</hi> For our parts, we are glad that we inſiſt upon the ſame way and method of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which the <hi>ſounder part of the Church</hi> hath ever uſed to encounter them withall.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:118623:34"/>
               <p>Surely our <hi>Saviour Chriſt</hi> better knew the way of proving <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>65</label> concluſions from Scripture, then you or we: And yet he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought it neceſſary to tye himſelf up to <hi>expreſſe Texts,</hi> but allowed himſelf the liberty of the <hi>interpretations</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions.</hi> When Satan tempted him to <hi>turn ſtones into bread,</hi> he thought it ſufficient to repell the Tentation, by that Text of <hi>Moſes, Man liveth not by bread alone, but by every word that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 4. 4. Deut. 8. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>proceedeth out of the mouth of God.</hi> The force of which <hi>Anſwer</hi> lies in this <hi>Syllogiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If God be able to ſupply the want of ordinary food, that a mans life ſhall be ſuſtained without it, whileſt God hath work for him to do, then ſhould I do ill, if (in diſtruſt of him) I ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand theſe ſtones to be made bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But God is thus able;</hi> for <hi>man lives not, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore <hi>I ſhould do ill, if I ſhould command theſe ſtones to be made bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had one of your Brethren been at the <hi>Devills</hi> elbow, he would have taught him more wit then to take ſuch an anſwer, and have turned him to put our Saviour upon the producing of an <hi>expreſſe Text</hi> of Scripture that forbad <hi>Jeſus</hi> the <hi>Son of Mary to command ſtones to be made bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So in the <hi>ſecond Tentation,</hi> both our <hi>Saviour</hi> and the <hi>Devill</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>66</label> alſo (if no <hi>meanings</hi> or <hi>deductions</hi> be allowable in urging of Scripture) might have gone to School to you. The <hi>Devill</hi> ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Scripture to our <hi>Saviour,</hi> to conclude the lawfulneſs of his <hi>caſting himſelf down from the Pinnacle:</hi> For (ſaith he) it is written, <hi>He ſhall give his Angels charge concerning thee, &amp;c.</hi> We do not find our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſo well verſed in your way of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as to deny his proof, becauſe it was not expreſly, <hi>God ſhall give his Angels charge over Jeſus the Son of Mary, and in their hands ſhall they beare him up, &amp;c.</hi> But anſwers by another Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to ſhew that that Text was not to be underſtood <hi>of prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in waies of tempting God, by running our ſelves upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary dangers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, when our Saviour had anſwered him with that place, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 16. <hi>Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God,</hi> Satan alſo was to ſeek of that plea which you could have ſuggeſted to him, <hi>Viz.</hi> That that Scripture did not expreſly forbid <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth to throw himſelf down from the Pinnacle.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:118623:34"/>
               <p>And in the <hi>third Tentation</hi> (according to your Tenet) our <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>67</label> 
                  <hi>Saviour</hi> had been hard put to it, to prove that it was unlawfull to worſhip the <hi>Devill</hi> himſelfe; had <hi>Satan</hi> been diſciplined by your principles, and required of him an expreſſe Text, <hi>That it is not lawfull to worſhip the Devill.</hi> Whereas it ſeemes for want of your Artifice, the ſilly Tempter was put off with a Scripture that requires us <hi>to worſhip and ſerve God onely,</hi> and concludes the unlawfulneſſe of <hi>Devill-worſhip</hi> by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If we muſt worſhip and ſerve God only,</hi> ergo <hi>not the Devill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But we muſt worſhip and ſerve God only, therefore not the Devill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>Sadduces</hi> afterwards were very <hi>ſilly animalls,</hi> that <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>68</label> they would let our <hi>Saviour</hi> go away in triumph for <hi>putting</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 32. Exod. 3. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>them to ſilence,</hi> by ſo weak a proof of the Reſurrection, as the words of God to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Buſh, <hi>I am the God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the God of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and the God of</hi> Jacob. Why had they not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired (in ſo fundamentall an Article of faith eſpecially) a poſitive and expreſſe Scripture, affirming in ſo many words, <hi>that the dead ſhall riſe againe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you think our <hi>Saviours</hi> example will not beare us out in <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>69</label> our <hi>interpretations</hi> and <hi>deductions,</hi> becauſe <hi>he was infallible in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>what he ſpake, and neither did nor could erre in what he ſaid; which,</hi> you ſuppoſe, <hi>cannot be ſaid of us, or our meanings, and arguments.</hi> To which we <hi>anſwer,</hi> we do not compare our ſelves with our Saviour in point of infallibility (although your generation do, who account themſelves equally perfect with him.) But this we ſay, that our Saviour in theſe places and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, where he argues from the Scriptures, doth not <hi>urge his owne infallibility,</hi> as the ground upon which he requires beleif, neither did Satan or the Sadduces <hi>acquieſce</hi> in the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, but in the conviction wrought in them by the ſtrength of his Arguments. And we muſt tell you, that <hi>any one</hi> who can draw an Argument <hi>rightly</hi> from Scripture, is no leſſe <hi>infallible</hi> in the concluſions <hi>ſo</hi> deduced thence, then our Saviour was in his. The queſtion therefore will be, <hi>Whether any perſon in interpreting and arguing from Scripture be infallible?</hi> but <hi>whether ſuch interpretations and deductions be truly, and</hi> bona fide
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:118623:35"/> 
                  <hi>according to the mind of the H. Choſt in Scripture, whether they be drawn by a perſon that is fallible or infallible?</hi> For be the perſon never ſo <hi>fallible</hi> that gives the interpretation, or drawes the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, yet if the interpretation be ſound, and the argument rightly concluded, he is <hi>therein infallible:</hi> For you cannot be altogether ignorant of that common Maxime, <hi>That nothing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ex veris poſsunt non niſi vera ſequi.</note> 
                  <hi>but truth can rightly follow from truth, and a falſe concluſion can never be regularly drawn from true premiſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that all that <hi>flouriſh</hi> which you afterwards make, is but a meer <hi>rhetoricall vapour,</hi> and ſignifies juſt nothing to an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>70</label> Reader. For whereas you bid us <hi>either tell the people</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>plainly, that we are infallible, that they may receive our deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from Scripture, for true Doctrine, nay Scripture it ſelf; or elſe ſay, that we are fallible, that ſo they may take liberty of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our actions and doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We <hi>anſwer,</hi> we need not <hi>tell the people we are infallible;</hi> and yet they are no leſſe bound to <hi>receive our deductions</hi> (if right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawne from Scripture) then if we were indeed ſo. Becauſe although we be not <hi>infallible,</hi> yet ſo far as we regularly argue from Scripture, we are <hi>not deceived,</hi> nor can <hi>deceive them.</hi> The authority of our deductions from Scripture, depends not on our fallibility or infallibility, but upon the evidence they carry in them, of their neceſſary connexion with the truth we argue from. And this becauſe we owne our ſelves fallible, we allow our hearers to uſe their owne judgments, and conſciences to prove and try whether it be ſo or no. God forbid but <hi>they who</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>muſt dye for themſelves, and account to the Lord for themſelves, ſhould interpret for themſelves and beleive for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelve?</hi> But what then? will it therefore follow that they muſt not receive our interpretations, or beleive our deductions? Or that we may not help them to interpret, or draw deductions, which they cannot ſo well do themſelves? They <hi>interpret for themſelves,</hi> that by the light of the Scriptures, and their owne Judgments led by them, ſee cauſe to <hi>owne our interpretations.</hi> And they <hi>beleive for themſelves,</hi> who are (upon a ſerious weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Arguments) convinced that they ought to <hi>admit them as juſt and lawfull deductions from Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What you add in the cloſe of that Paragraph, that it may ſo <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>71</label>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:118623:35"/> fall out, that <hi>ſix of thoſe that eſteem themſelves the ableſt Doctors, if ſhut aſunder, ſhall ſo vary in the interpretation of one Scripture, that ſcarce two of the ſix ſhall agree in the ſame interpretation;</hi> Whence you would infer <hi>how little credit is to be given to our deductions:</hi> we might take for an <hi>unſavoury ſcoff.</hi> and ſo paſſe it by. But we ſhall forgive you this, and many more ſuch, if it will do you any good, and vouchſafe to anſwer, even where you deſerve no <hi>anſwer</hi> but <hi>ſilence</hi> and <hi>ſcorne.</hi> Be it therefore as you ſay (which yet in Scriptures that containe matter of ſaith and practiſe, we cannot ſuppoſe; moſt of us, we conceive, in ſuch, <hi>are,</hi> at leaſt (till the new-fangled conceits of theſe times infected ſome of the Miniſtry, as well as others) <hi>were,</hi> of the ſame mind in moſt of them) yet herein we are no more to be blamed then the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and other <hi>primitive Teachers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who differed as much in thoſe times of cleareſt light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Scriptures that enjoyned the obſervation of <hi>Jewiſh Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies;</hi> whileſt ſome of them earneſtly contended, that they extended to converted Gentiles, and others affirmed the quite contrary. And will you thence conclude, <hi>that there is little credit to be given to any of their deductions, becauſe they diſagreed among themſelves?</hi> All that can be hence ſolidly inferred, is no more but this, that therefore it concernes Gods people to <hi>ſearch</hi> (with the <hi>Noble Beroeans)</hi> whether the things, the <hi>one</hi> or the <hi>other</hi> ſaith, be moſt conſonant to the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>But you that will not beleive <hi>our interpretations,</hi> or <hi>deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>72</label> becauſe we are not in <hi>all things agreed;</hi> will you beleive them in thoſe things wherein we are all, or the greateſt part of us of a mind: Surely, if ſo, moſt of the <hi>quaking Doctrines</hi> will fall to the ground; for very few, if any of us, ſhall dare to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret Scriptures to the countenance of thoſe horrid Doctrines before mentioned.</p>
               <p>In a word, this whole diſcourſe about <hi>infallibility,</hi> and <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>73</label> among our ſelves in interpretation of Scripture (as one hath very well obſerved before us) ſmells rank of your <hi>Popiſh</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Baxtet, <hi>Quakers Catechiſm.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tutors.</hi> For are they not the very ſame things which they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt us? <hi>That we have not an infalliable Spirit to interpret Scriptures, and that we differ among our ſelves in our interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> and therefore when we appeale to Scripture, as the only
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:118623:36"/> 
                  <hi>Judge of Controverſies</hi> between us; they (as you do) deny it upon this account, becauſe we have no infallible Spirit to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the Scriptures controverted, and thereby give an Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative deciſion of them. And what we anſwer to them, we therefore ſay to you in a word, <hi>The Scripture we owne as our onely Rule, and Judge in matters of faith; and we owne no inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Scripture, nor deſire others to owne any, but ſuch as hold proportion with other Scriptures;</hi> and ſuch interpretations and deductions are ſo far infallible, as they do neceſſarily agree to them, or follow from them.</p>
               <p>But (ſay you further) <hi>You have ſome of you been Teachers in</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>73</label> 
                  <hi>this Nation, ten, twenty, thirty yeares: were thoſe things that you have taught ſo many yeares together, neceſſarily deduced from Scripture?</hi> What then? <hi>If not</hi> (ſay you) <hi>then by your owne confeſſion you have taught falſehood.</hi> But ſtay, <hi>Sir,</hi> every dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that is not <hi>neceſſarily</hi> drawne from Scripture, is not <hi>falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</hi> A <hi>true concluſion</hi> may have but a <hi>probable conſequence</hi> ſometimes to infer it from the premiſſes. Its <hi>truth</hi> is never the leſſe for that, but its <hi>evidence.</hi> But ſuppoſe we ſhould <hi>confeſſe</hi> (for once) that <hi>all which we deduce from Scripture is not true?</hi> We know not what uſe you will make of it, except this, that thoſe that do not <hi>alwaies</hi> ſpeak truth, are not to be thought at <hi>any time</hi> to do ſo. And if ſo, we know whom this inference will hit as well as our ſelves. What think you of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> whom <hi>Paul withſtood to his face, Gal.</hi> 2. 11. for countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the falſe brethren in the Doctrine and practiſe of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicall Ordinances</hi> among the <hi>Gentile Churches,</hi> and <hi>compelling the Gentiles to live as the Jewes?</hi> was he <hi>never</hi> in the <hi>right,</hi> or not to be beleived to be ſo, becauſe he was <hi>then</hi> in the <hi>wrong?</hi> Nay, doth not God himſelfe ſuppoſe a poſſibility of being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the beſt of his Miniſters, when he bids hearers <hi>prove all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 21. and commends the <hi>Beroeans</hi> for <hi>ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, whether the things that</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Silas <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were ſo or no? Act.</hi> 17. 11. We ſuppoſe that no godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter will preach that, which he <hi>knowes to be falſe.</hi> But if <hi>without his knowledge</hi> (yea, or <hi>with his knowledge)</hi> any one ſhould do ſo; it is the hearers fault if he be deceived thereby, becauſe he hath a certain rule whereby to examine what he teacheth; and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:118623:36"/> we profeſſe we deſire no further to be credited then the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will beare us out in what we ſay.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe there be ſome of us poſſibly to be found, who <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>74</label> will juſtifie <hi>all that they have preached for ſo long time, to be truth neceſſarily deduced from Scripture:</hi> What of that? Why? <hi>then</hi> (ſay you) <hi>all that is ſo taught is infallible.</hi> True; And what then? Forſooth, then (you add) <hi>why do you not then adjoyn all your Sermons to the Scripture; for if neceſſarily deduced from Scripture, they are Scripture, and a part of the Saints rule:</hi> And ſo (you go on) <hi>it would become ſo voluminous a Book, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poore Soules Eſtates would not buy a Bible.</hi> We ſhall give you a breif account why we do not, if it may do you ſervice, And that is, becauſe we do not judge our ſelves ſo immediatly inſpired in our Sermons (although we deliver the ſame truths) the <hi>holy Pen-men of God</hi> were in penning of the Scriptures. The ſacred Writers of Scripture, did not onely write the things they left upon record to the Church, by immediate inſpiration, but the <hi>words and phraſes</hi> in which they expreſſed them. Whereas the beſt Miniſters that ſince have been, have been faine to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe thoſe truths in notions and tearmes of their owne; yea, and the Apoſtles themſelves in their popular Sermons. And therefore, we ſuppoſe, the H. Ghoſt thought not fit to record all the <hi>popular Sermons</hi> which were preached by the Apoſtles <hi>themſelves,</hi> but only appointed them to draw up the ſumme of the Doctrine they generally taught in expreſſions <hi>of their owne,</hi> into a forme of ſound words of <hi>his owne</hi> inſpiration, to be a <hi>Standard of Doctrine and expreſſion</hi> to ſucceeding ages.</p>
               <p>And yet, ſuppoſing the Apoſtles alwaies <hi>preached</hi> as they <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>75</label> 
                  <hi>wrote</hi> (by immediate inſpiration) as to <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>forme;</hi> then we ask you, <hi>Why they did not bind up all their Sermons with the Canonicall Scriptures,</hi> ſeeing <hi>all they taught was infallible?</hi> Whatever you anſwer hereunto, will be applied to our caſe. But we ſuppoſe <hi>John</hi> gives you a ſufficient reaſon in the cloſe of his Goſpel, <hi>There are many other things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which Jeſus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jo. 21. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>did, which if they ſhould be written every one, I ſuppoſe that even the World it ſelfe would not containe the Bookes that ſhould be written.</hi> So that God therefore thought fit to keep from after Ages, part of the <hi>Hiſtory of Chriſt,</hi> that the Bible might not be
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:118623:37"/> too voluminous. And we hope, the ſame reaſon will ſerve for us, if we do not <hi>bind up our neceſſary and infallible deductions with the Bible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word, this queſtion is propoſed with no greater meaſure <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>76</label> of diſcretion, then if you ſhould ask, <hi>Whether all the Buſhells, and Yards, and Pints in every mans houſe or ſhop in</hi> Briſtoll <hi>be exact meaſure, or no?</hi> If all, ſay <hi>yee:</hi> then you further enquire; <hi>Why they do not all bring them into the Market-houſe, or publick place appointed for that purpoſe, and chaine them all to the common Standard, ſeeing they are all alike exact with it?</hi> Surely to ſuch a <hi>wiſe queſtion,</hi> the <hi>anſwer</hi> will be eaſie, <hi>Viz. Becauſe one pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Standard is enough to meaſure private Meaſures by; and the ſeverall Tradeſmen according to their ſeverall imployments, having once had their private Meaſures tryed by that, can make profitable uſe of them at home.</hi> We ſhall leave you to make the application to the Queſtion in hand.</p>
               <p>But before we diſmiſſe this captious Argument of yours, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>77</label> you ſhall give us leave to <hi>retort</hi> it upon you, and then ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you can give a wiſer anſwer to your <hi>owne question</hi> in your <hi>owne caſe,</hi> then we have done in <hi>ours.</hi> We ask therefore. <hi>Is all that</hi> George Fox, James Nayler, <hi>or your ſelfe teach, write, and pronounce as from God</hi> (For from Scripture you will not ſay you ſpeak, ſeeing that it is not your rule of Doctrine) <hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily true, or no?</hi> If <hi>not,</hi> then (by your owne confeſſion) <hi>you have</hi> (if your owne Argument be good) <hi>taught falſehood;</hi> if <hi>ſo;</hi> then <hi>all you and they have taught is infallible;</hi> for you ſay, it is dictated by the ſame Spirit that indited the Scriptures, and ſo equall to them (your Epiſtles are as good as St. <hi>Pauls</hi> is before-ſaid by ſome of you.) And then <hi>why do you not adjoyne all your Preachments and Pamphlets to the Bible? &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the <hi>practiſe</hi> of our <hi>Saviour Chriſt</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>78</label> his <hi>infallibility,</hi> which we pretend not to) is and ought to be herein our <hi>example.</hi> But we need not defend our practiſe with ſo great a name, having the examples of ſo many <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and other <hi>primitive Teachers</hi> to plead for us. We pray you tell us (otherwiſe) how the Apoſtles <hi>proved by the Scriptures that Jeſus was the Chriſt?</hi> Did they, or could they bring any one Text in all the <hi>old Teſtament</hi> that ſaith ſo <hi>in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:118623:37"/> That Jeſus the Son of</hi> Mary, <hi>berne in</hi> Bethlem, <hi>is the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Act. 17. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Meſſiah?</hi> No, but the Text tells us; that they <hi>opened</hi> the Scriptures, and <hi>laid them one by another</hi> in a way of reaſoning, (as the word rendred <hi>alledging</hi> ſignifies in the Originall) and ſo convinced the Jewes. How will you diſpute with a <hi>Jew,</hi> that ownes not the infallibility of the Pen-men of the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and ſo will queſtion the truth of what is there affirmed, that <hi>this Jeſus is the Chriſt?</hi> you have no Weapon to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him withall, but <hi>Argument</hi> and <hi>deductions</hi> from the <hi>old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament:</hi> For did the old Teſtament <hi>expreſly</hi> ſay ſo any where, the queſtion were at an end between us and him.</p>
               <p>We intreat you further to tell us, how the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>79</label> makes good his aſſertion concerning the lawfulneſſe of his and <hi>Barnabaſſes</hi> requiring, and receiving maintenance out of the Law, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 8. <hi>Say I theſe things as a man, i. e.</hi> by mine own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate judgment, or <hi>ſaith not the Law the ſame alſo.</hi> We pray you tell us where the Law ſaith in ſo many words, <hi>that</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas <hi>might lawfully forbeare working,</hi> &amp; expect to <hi>eat the fruit of the Vineyard they planted? &amp;c.</hi> Sure we are, the place quoted by him out of the Law, ſaith no more but this, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the Corne, v.</hi> 9. Here is not a word of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> except <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> be <hi>Oxen</hi> (would a <hi>Quaker</hi> reply.) But though the Text ſpeak <hi>expreſly of Oxen,</hi> yet the Apoſtle finds <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> in the <hi>reaſon and equity</hi> of that Law; and ſo makes a ſtrong Argument of it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>And ſurely it will prove an hard matter to your ſelf, or your <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>80</label> Companions, to draw forth to any rationall man the <hi>Dectrines of election</hi> and <hi>reprobation,</hi> out of <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. 23. &amp; <hi>Mal.</hi> 1, 2, 3. quoted for the proof thereof by that Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 11, 12, 13. and the <hi>righteouſneſſe of theſe decrees</hi> out of <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 19. and many other Doctrines of affinity with them, in that Chapter, out of the reſt of the <hi>old Teſtament Texts</hi> there alledged, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>conſequences;</hi> We are ſure none of them all are in <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe termes</hi> in thoſe Scriptures brought to prove them. We might add the proofes that the Author to the Hebrews brings for the <hi>Godhead of Chriſt,</hi> from <hi>Pſa.</hi> 45. 6, 7. 102. 25. &amp; 110. 1.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:118623:38"/> quoted, Chap. 1. 8. 9. 10. 13. and the <hi>Eternity of Chriſts Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> from the Hiſtory of <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> and <hi>Pſa.</hi> 110. 4. quoted Chap. 7.</p>
               <p>But we foreſeee, that the queſtion will ſtill be between us, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>81</label> 
                  <hi>Whether we be infallible</hi> (as the Apoſtles are ſuppoſed to have been) <hi>in our interpretations and deductions?</hi> For anſwer where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, we refer you to what was even now ſaid on this point. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here we crave leave to add, that we have reaſon to think <hi>our</hi> infallibility and <hi>yours</hi> is much at a rate: And yet we find <hi>you</hi> very frequently taking that liberty which you deny <hi>us.</hi> For how do you conceive the <hi>Propheſies of Micha</hi> againſt thoſe that <hi>taught for hire,</hi> and the <hi>woes of our Saviour,</hi> againſt thoſe that <hi>do their workes to be ſeen of men, and ſtand praying in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and love the uppermoſt roomes at Feaſts, and greetings in the Markets, &amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>commands</hi> given to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of Chriſt that then were ſent by him upon a ſpeciall errand, of <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving freely what they freely received, &amp;c.</hi> concerne us, whoſe names are not expreſly mentioned in thoſe Texts, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction or argumentation, ſuch as it is? Nay, how do you bring downe the prohibitions of <hi>calling men Maſters, respecting of perſons, &amp;c.</hi> to be obliging to you, and your Proſelites, but by <hi>conſequence?</hi> Were it not eaſie for us (were we minded to play the ſame <hi>Childs play</hi> with you which you do with us) to require of you an <hi>expreſſe</hi> place of Scripture, forbidding <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Speed</hi> by name, to do thus and thus: or at leaſt <hi>every Chriſtian</hi> or <hi>Diſciple?</hi> and yet then you would need a deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to bring downe the prohibition to your ſelfe in particular, ſuch as this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No Chriſtian, or Diſciple of Chriſt muſt call men Maſters. But T. S. is a Chriſtian.</hi> We wiſh he were.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore T. S. muſt not call men Maſters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay (to go yet further with you) we might very well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>82</label> of you an expreſſe Scripture for your two fundamentall Articles, <hi>That Chriſt is the light that enlightens every one that comes into the World; and that Chriſt is the word of God, and not to the Scriptures.</hi> A good friend of yours in a diſcourſe <note place="margin">T. C.</note> with one of us, having before denied all <hi>conſequences</hi> and <hi>dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> from Scripture, as you do; was pittifully gravelled, when
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:118623:38"/> he was required to produce expreſſe Scriptures to prove theſe propoſitions, and was told that the Texts he produced, which were Jo. 8. 12. <hi>I am the light of the World,</hi> and Jo. 1. 9. <hi>That was the true light which enlightneth every one that comes into the World,</hi> had not the name of Chriſt in them, but it was to be concluded by Argument, that thoſe words are ſpoken of Chriſt; and that the place, <hi>Jo.</hi> 1. 1. did not expreſly affirme that <hi>Chriſt is the word:</hi> but is onely inferred thence by deductions. And (as for <hi>meanings</hi> and <hi>interpretations)</hi> it was none of the beſt, which the <hi>ſame party</hi> gave of that Scripture, which forbids the Diſciples to <hi>carry ſhooes,</hi> as well as a <hi>Purſe</hi> or <hi>Scrip</hi> (whence he was told, that it as much concerned <hi>G. Fox</hi> to go without <hi>ſhooes,</hi> as <hi>us</hi> without <hi>Purſe</hi> or <hi>Scrip) Viz. That the Text for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids to</hi> carry <hi>ſhooes, but not to</hi> weare them. A learned interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and ſuch as becomes your infallibility! And your ſelfe, however unlawfull you judge it in us to interpret Scripture, yet <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>83</label> more then once undertake it very <hi>Dictator-like;</hi> as <hi>p.</hi> 8. where you interpret the word <hi>Rule, Gal.</hi> 6. 16. for the <hi>rule of the new Creature,</hi> not the Scriptures (as if the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and the <hi>rule of the new Creature</hi> were oppoſites:) and ſo <hi>p.</hi> 19. where you interpret the <hi>Record</hi> ſpoken of 1. <hi>Jo.</hi> 5. 10. to be <hi>eternall life,</hi> not the Scriptures: and againe, <hi>p.</hi> 20. you interpret the <hi>foundation</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 20. to be <hi>that ſame Jeſus, who was preached by the Prophets and Apoſtles.</hi> So hard a matter it is for men that undertake to give Law to others, not to tranſgreſſe it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and not to conceit <hi>the caſe altered</hi> in their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, from what they rigorouſly pronounce concerning others!</p>
               <p>We have not yet quite done with you, and therefore we muſt <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>84</label> crave your patience a little longer, whileſt we ask you a few plaine <hi>Queſtions</hi> upon this ſubject now at hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 1. <hi>Sir,</hi> you will admit of <hi>no interpretations</hi> of Scripture, we entreat you therefore to tell us. <hi>Chriſt ſaith, he is the true Vine, and his Father an Husbandman, Jo.</hi> 15. 1. Are they <hi>properly</hi> ſo, or <hi>Metaphorically?</hi> If you ſay <hi>metaphorically,</hi> or <hi>improperly,</hi> you interpret; for the Texts expreſſe words are not, <hi>I am a metaphoricall Vine, and my Father a metaphoricall Husbandman.</hi> If you ſay <hi>properly,</hi> you blaſpheme.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:118623:39"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 2. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the door,</hi> Jo. 10. 9. <hi>You beleive,</hi> you <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſtle, p.</hi> 7.</note> ſay, that <hi>Chriſt meanes as he ſpeakes, and therefore you deny our meanings and interpretations as needleſſe.</hi> Is Chriſt then that which we in propriety of ſpeech call a <hi>door?</hi> If you ſay, he is <hi>in a ſpirituall ſence</hi> a door; who <hi>interprets</hi> now? Do we offend, if we interpret this Text, of a <hi>ſpirituall door</hi> to a <hi>myſticall build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and you though you give the ſame ſenſe, not ſo?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 3. Nay, what ſay you further to thoſe two places of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> which in <hi>words</hi> flatly contradict one another. <hi>Yee ſee,</hi> ſaith <hi>James, that by workes a man is juſtified, and not by faith onely, Ja.</hi> 2. 24. But <hi>we know,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, That a man is not juſtified by the workes of the Law, but by the faith of Jeſus Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 2. 16. You will allow (vve hope) that the Scriptures are <hi>truth,</hi> though they be not the <hi>word of God.</hi> Now truth, and truth, contradict not each other; ſo that vve muſt find a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſenſe from the contexts of both places, wherein the one <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes</hi> that works juſtifie not, and the other that they do.</p>
               <p>This reconciliation is uſually made by our Divines thus; St. <hi>Paul</hi> denies works to conſtitute any perſon <hi>juſt before God,</hi> and <hi>James</hi> affirmes, that workes declare a perſon <hi>juſt.</hi> How you <hi>(without interpretation)</hi> vvill reconcile them, we know not; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when vve conſider that you are a greater friend to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutive juſtification by workes</hi> (if you be of the mind of your fellow Quakers then vve believe <hi>James</hi> was, and ſo are more concerned to ſtudy how to come off fairely with <hi>Paul</hi> then vve.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 4. And now vve are upon the point of <hi>reconciling Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> vve ſhall make you a little more work in this kind. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The Father is greater then I,</hi> and yet he ſaith againe, <hi>I and the Father are one:</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of him, That <hi>he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted it no Robbery to be equall with God, Phil.</hi> 2. 9. The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>There are three that heare record in Heaven, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word, and the H. Ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</hi> Shew us (without interpretation) how Chriſt can be <hi>equall with the Father without robbery,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> with him, and yet the <hi>Father greater then he,</hi> how the <hi>Father, the word, and the H. Ghoſt</hi> can be <hi>three</hi> and yet <hi>one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we might here alſo put you the queſtion that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118623:39"/> put to the Phariſees. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 41. How Chriſt, is <hi>Davids Son,</hi> and yet <hi>Davids Lord?</hi> and we ſuppoſe with the ſame ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe <hi>that you will never be able to Anſwer us a word,</hi> if you hold your Principle of denying all interpretations, but that your forehead poſſibly may be harder then the Phariſees.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 5. What will you ſay to a Papiſt, (but that you owne not the Scripture, as a rule of Doctrine, which indeed is a quick way of Anſwering all difficult Texts) when he tells you that he finds Tranſubſtantiation in <hi>this is my body?</hi> Is the expreſſion <hi>proper,</hi> or <hi>figurative?</hi> was the <hi>bread</hi> his <hi>body indeed,</hi> or a <hi>Signe</hi> of it? if you ſay his body indeed, you are a Papiſt, if not you interprete.</p>
               <p>Sir to be ſhort, we ſhall take leave to mind you of theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and we have done.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to that un-chriſtian paſſage of yours <hi>[viz.</hi> a <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe beyond the Stars,</hi> a <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> far above us] as you call the Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt in a ſlighting manner (and we have juſt ground to feare, ſome of thoſe you plead for ſpeake to that purpoſe in a ſpighting way) we heartily adviſe you to take heed what you doe, that you may not be found in the number of thoſe who by wicked hands labour to pull the Crowne from the Head of Jeſus, and deſtroy the very being of Holyneſſe amongſt men, for all the workes of ſuch Perſons at the beſt are but beautifull deformities, and although they may be <hi>highly eſteemed</hi> amongſt men, yet they are <hi>abomination</hi> before the Holy God; for our parts we <hi>are not aſhamed of the</hi> Goſpell of Chriſt, and have (through mercy) <hi>determined not to know</hi> any thing amongſt our People but Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified: and we judge it a ſpeciall duty in this ſeaſon (the Lord helpe us in it) that the more you and your complices doe either wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly reflect upon, or downe right Blaſpheme and ſpeake againſt that Glorious Righteouſneſſe, the more to exalt, and make mention of that Righteouſneſſe, even that only.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas you ſay <hi>[could the Scripture be a rule before it</hi> was Scripture?] We anſwer, the word now written, even the ſelfe ſame word was the very ſame, and had the ſame Office <hi>viz.</hi> to be a Divine <hi>ground</hi> of faith and <hi>rule</hi> of life before it was written; as for inſtance, <hi>Enochs</hi> Prophecie quoted by <hi>Jude</hi> 14. 15 concerning the judge, the attendants, the Perſons to be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the judgement it ſelfe, the deeds and words for which they are judged, is the very ſame with the written word; and Gods
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:118623:40"/> word to <hi>Abraham Gen</hi> 17. 1. <hi>I am God al-ſufficient, waelke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, and be upright,</hi> is the ſame with, nay is the ſumme of the written word, yet this was ſpoken foure hundred yeares before a word was committed to writing, it being generally agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was the firſt holy man that did write by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt Pray Sir tell us what difference was there between the Law as <hi>ſpoken</hi> by the <hi>mouth</hi> of God, and afterwards <hi>written</hi> by the <hi>finger</hi> of God? When <hi>Moſes</hi> being provoked in the buſineſſe of the Golden Calfe had broken the two Tables, God commanded him to make two Tables of Stone more, and the Text tells us that God did write the very ſelfe ſame words that he had written before in the firſt Tables <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 1. the Truth is you doe but trifle in your Quaerie, yet we feare you border not far from Blaſphemy, you nuſle up your quaking freinds in their horrid rejecting of the Scriptures to be the rule, and ſo make them liſten after inſpirations, you would make void the word of God through your pretended Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and pull that pure and perfect clear Light out of the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Aſſembleis, that men might follow the <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of their darkned minds, and deceitfull hearts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You quaere, <hi>Whether our Sermons are infallible, and if ſo, why they are not bound up with the Bible, and if ſo, how huge a Volume would it make, and how few could buy it?</hi> we reply, the Doctrine which we Preach is not ours, but Gods, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore infallible, but muſt they therefore be bound up with the Bible. what think you of the Sermons of Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 21. <hi>Luke</hi> 5. 3. were they not infallible? or the Sermon <hi>Philip</hi> Preached to the <hi>Eunuch</hi> out of <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 53. or that <hi>Paul</hi> Preached at his farewell <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. were they not infallibly true? yet theſe were not bound up with the Bible, why doe you thus from your inward darkneſſe cavill at outward Light? we call it your darkneſſe, hoping that you doe not knowingly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the truth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As for Miniſters Maintenance, upon which you harpe ſo much, as knowing the ſound to be very welcome to the eares of your gang and others, we deſire this favour at your hands, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoberly to anſwer our reaſons, or elſe to be ſo ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as to forbeare your ſcoffings.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As for your defence of the Language <hi>[thee and thou</hi>] we referr you to what is ſaid a bove, we ſhall only add this, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:118623:40"/> think it to be any ſuch great Crime to ſpeake in this one caſe the plural <hi>you</hi> for <hi>thou,</hi> for the ſingular, as when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies <hi>we</hi> for <hi>I,</hi> as <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 9 <hi>we are perſwaded better things of you, and though we thus ſpeake,</hi> and againe, <hi>we deſire v.</hi> 11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, wheras as you ſay in favour of your deare Quakers <hi>[theſe are the Practices for which they are hated</hi>] as though they were ſo innocent: we reply, beſides their Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, of which before, and their railings, curſings, ſlanders, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, we deſire to know what you think of foure or five inſtances we ſhall propoſe; firſt, what doe you think of the Quaker that acted <hi>that moſt abominable, unnameable ſin with a Mare?</hi> what doe you think of it, was it not from his light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? or what is your opinion of another poore wretch, that hanged himſelfe? theſe two you may find at large added to the relation of <hi>Gilpin</hi> of <hi>Kendall,</hi> and confeſſed by the Prime of that way to be true; what may be your thoughts of thoſe Quakers that killed their Mother? it was thus, they were taught to harken to, and follow after the Light within them, this Light taught them they ought to deſtroy the <hi>Originall of Sin,</hi> and by the ſaid Light they apprehended their <hi>Mother</hi> to be the <hi>Originall,</hi> and from thence ſtill by the ſaid Light they moſt wickedly embrued their hands in the blood of their Mother, this you may read in Mr. <hi>William Keyes</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Stokeſly</hi> his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to eighteen Quaeries who was with them in Priſon.</p>
               <p>What may be your judgement of <hi>Nicholas Kate</hi> of <hi>Harwell</hi> in this County of Berks? who about ten months ſince came into <hi>Newberry</hi> between eight and nine in the Morning on the Lord; day, <hi>ſtarke naked in a</hi> moſt immodeſt manner, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Pagans, and ſo walked through a long Street, only with <hi>an inchanted belt about him</hi> (which belt we have ground to call inchanted,) this man did not converſe or live as a Husband with his wife for many months before this, we will tell you what his Doctrines were.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That Marriage was made by man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That Chriſtians were worſe then Beaſts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That any woman was as free to him as his Wife:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>That his wife was no wife of his, ſhe was a limb of the Devil.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>That he was holy, and</hi> all things <hi>that he toucht were ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as his very Hatchet, his pot, his knife.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:118623:41"/>
                  <item>6. <hi>That when the fulnes of time was come he ſhould work miracles.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>This man hath left his owne family his Land and ſtock of a very conſiderable value, entred upon by Perſons whom the Country eſteemeth Ranters, his wife a weake diſeaſed woman, who brought him a valuable portion, left to the mercies of theſe Perſons, which are cruell enough to her, the farmer <hi>Kate</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſince his departure was never heard of by his wife or any of her freinds, if any Perſon can tell where he is, or what is become of him, they may doe a charitable Chriſtian Office to informe his much diſtreſſed Wife. Laſtly, what doe you think of one of your neighbours of <hi>Briſtoll</hi> who lately even the 29. of <hi>Aprill</hi> laſt at <hi>Marleborough</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts</hi> in a diſcourſe with a Godly, diſcreet, and Learned freind, held out this Light,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>He knew no ſuch thing as the reſurrection of the body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That the body of Chriſt was not in Heaven, neither ſhould he come thence with a body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>He defended thoſe that went naked, but as yet, he had no command to doe ſo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>That of late he went to bed with a woman who was not his wife, and that he did it without Sin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>That that very Chriſt crucified at Jeruſalem, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling in him.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>That he was confident of his perfect holineſſe,</hi> and on that account <hi>went to bed with the woman, and yet</hi> afterwards excuſed himſelfe <hi>ſaying, there was a neceſſity for it, there was no other ſpare bed in the Houſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Sir, theſe, with thoſe before recited, are the Doctrins and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that we according to the meaſure received contend againſt; all the hurt we wiſh you is this, that God would give you the ſpirit of truth love, and of a ſound mind, that you may not go on to vilify the Lord of Glory, to ſlight the word of life, truth and ſalvation, and ſhoot your Tart, indeed bitter ſpeeches like darts againſt men that feare God, and deſire to prize and keep cloſe to the word of his grace; for our parts we have a witneſſe within, that what we have done, is for the truth, which we pray, that you and we may receive in the love of it, and in ſo doing, we ſhall ſubſcribe our ſelves,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Reding</hi> 
                     <date>this 12 of <hi>May</hi> 1656.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your Freinds,
<list>
                        <item>Chriſtopher Fowler.</item>
                        <item>Simon Ford.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
